<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A newe yeares gift for the suole [sic], or A christian meditation of Christs incarnation Preached in the Cathedrall Church at Norwich on Christmasse day last. 1614. By Samuel Garey, preacher of Gods word at Winfarthing.</title>
            <author>Garey, Samuel, 1582 or 3-1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115876</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851093</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851093</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16348</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01474)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16348)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1099:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A newe yeares gift for the suole [sic], or A christian meditation of Christs incarnation Preached in the Cathedrall Church at Norwich on Christmasse day last. 1614. By Samuel Garey, preacher of Gods word at Winfarthing.</title>
                  <author>Garey, Samuel, 1582 or 3-1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Ssansby [sic], for Henry Fetherstone,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A new-yeeres gift for the soule.</note>
                  <note>Some pages stained, affecting print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16348:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16348:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEWE YEARES GIFT FOR THE SVOLE, OR <hi>A Chriſtian Meditation of Chriſts</hi> INCARNATION.</p>
            <p>Preached in the Cathedrall Church at NORWICH <hi>on Chriſtmaſſe day laſt.</hi> 1614.</p>
            <p>By SAMVEL GAREY, Preacher of GODS word at WYN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ARTHING.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LVKE. 10.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I hold, I bring you tidings of great ioy, that ſhall be to all people: that vnto you is borne that dyy in the Citie of <hi>DAVID</hi> a Sauiour, which is <hi>CHRIST</hi> the <hi>LORD.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ISOST. HOM. 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; quomodo factum ſit, neſcio, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ignorati</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>That is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> was made fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is was made, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ew not, &amp; what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by WILLIAM SEA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16348:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16348:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, SIR THOMAS HOLLAND Knight, and his vertuous LADIE: all tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, <hi>and ſpirituall happineſse.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>(RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL)</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue preſumed to ſeale this Sermon with the Signet of your names, that your worthineſſe might giue luſtre to this worthles labor: and I was induced by many Allectiues to gratifie you with this ſmall remembrance: Firſt, your religious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and affection you beare, and emboſome to our tribe of <hi>Leui.</hi> Secondly, your Cordiall loue, and continuall deuotion you manifeſt vnto the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. Thirdly, you are the viue Image of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted father, a Foſter-father of the Clergie, who
<pb facs="tcp:16348:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:16348:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:16348:4"/> now reſteth with the Father of glorie, from whom I receiued the firſt fruits of my poore liuing: and therefore, as a due debt, I tender vnto you the firſt fruits of my ſmall learning: Accept it as a gratefull Teſtimony of a thankefull minde,
<q>Qui ſi non potui maxima, parua dedi:</q> not the greatneſſe of the gift, but the gratefulneſſe of the Giuer is to bee reſpected:<note place="margin">Caſſio.</note> and as one well ſpeakes, <hi>Inuitat ad magna, qui grate accipit modica:</hi> So your gentle acceptance ſhall encourage me to ſome greater buſineſſe: and as the Apoſtle ſpeakes of Almes,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 8.12.</note> So in this Action, <hi>If firſt there be a willing mind, it is accepted according to that a man hath, and not accord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng to that he hath not:</hi> And as we reade, when the Tabernacle was to be built by <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 25.2.</note> 
               <hi>Euery one brought ſome thing, ſome more, ſome leſſe, ſome better, ſome worſe, and all neceſſary:</hi> So for the building of Gods Church, euery one ſhould bring ſuch as they haue,<note place="margin">Lul. 21.2, 3.</note> ſome Talents, and ſome with the <hi>Widow, mites to caſt into the Treaſurie:</hi> and although in theſe flouriſhing dayes of learning, there is a Satiety of worthy writers, yet they cannot breede a ſurfet: for we cannot ſay of ſpirituall oblation, as the wiſe men ſaid to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the bountifull times of popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar oblation,<note place="margin">Exod. 36.5.</note> 
               <hi>The people bring too much, and more then enough for the vſe of the worke, &amp;c.</hi> No: all our h nds, hearts, and tongues were giuen vs to this end,<note place="margin">Aliis micans, meipſum conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo.</note> to ſpend them as ſelfe-conſuming lampes, to giue light to others: and therefore not to ſhew my ſelfe defectiue in this publike ſeruice, (which was ſo begged by many to bee publiſhed) and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> confeſſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non licet habere
<pb facs="tcp:16348:4"/> cognitionem priuatam, ne priuemur eâ:</hi> Wee muſt not make our knowledge priuate, leſt we be depriued of it. I haue aduentured to preſent this Trauell to the generall eye of men, hoping that the graine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, it doth better in the market, then in the garner. If any one Soule ſhall receiue good by it; I ſhall be fully ſatisfied, and your Worſhip ſhall be intereſſed in the claime of that comfort.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Iacob, when he left his ſonnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 49.28.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed them with a ſeuerall Bleſsing:</hi> So doe I beſeech God, the giuer of all gifts, to beſtow a ſpirituall Benediction vpon this labour, and to giue increaſe to that doctrine, which we here plant and water: and ſo in all ſubmiſſion, I commit this to your Patronage, and commend you to Gods good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>At your Seruice in the Lord, SAMVEL GAREY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16348:5"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN, AND COVRTEOVS READER, SAVING GRACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He importunitie of many, who heard this Sermon deliuered, and ſollicited me to haue it publiſhed, were preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling motiues with me to take this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie in offering it to the world, thinking of Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> ſpeech, <hi>Qui rectum facere cùm poſſit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de libero arbitr.</note> 
               <hi>non vult, amittat poſſe, cum velit,</hi> Hee that will not doe good, when hee may, let him want power when he would. So I hope, this ſhall doe good to them that are good. Wherein I hunt not after vulgar commendation, which is like childrens loue, gotten, and forgotten in an howre: neither did I euer affect, that my ſelfe, or my labours ſhould bee pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a Cogniſance to the Towne-coat, or to depend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the common ſleeue of popular iudgement. And indeed I am ſomwhat of <hi>Socrates</hi> mind in <hi>Plato,</hi> who euermore ſuſpected that for bad, which the common people extolled for good: and as <hi>Plinie</hi> gaue it a rule in Schoole, that hee declaymed worſt,<note place="margin">Prou 25.11.</note> who was applauded moſt. Yet <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> thus farre will giue this a commendation, that they were <hi>words vttered in due ſeaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I offer this to temperate men, ſtudious, ingenuous, and zealous men: for, as for Criticall, or hypocriticall, I
<pb facs="tcp:16348:5"/> neuer loued to prayſe them, or pleaſe them. I ſay here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in with <hi>Cicero,</hi> Perſeum <hi>non curo legere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cice. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Orat.</note> Laelium <hi>volo: Perſeus</hi> is too learned, I wiſh honeſt, and not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned <hi>Laelius</hi> to bee my Reader: for I contemne the iniudicious cenſure of meere Ignorants.<note place="margin">Sen prou.</note> 
               <hi>Graue iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt eius, qui iudicare non poteſt:</hi> the ignoranter man, the ſeuerer Iudge: to ſtand to ſuch Iudges, were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand to condemne my ſelfe.<note place="margin">Iaert. in vita Anacharſ.</note> 
               <hi>Anacharſis</hi> miſliked it in Greece, and ſo doe I here with vs, <hi>Artifices cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, iudicant qui non ſunt artifices:</hi> Diuines preach in the pulpit, Artizans prate, and iudge of it in the Ale-houſe: But for the honest and well minded Reader, who is neither captious, or curious,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>But delights in the Law of the Lord, and meditates therein day and night:</hi> who labours to purchaſe knowledge by diligence, and by his deuotion to redeeme time, and not misſpend it in idle pleaſure, which one compares to Hawking, much coſt,<note place="margin">D. Boys.</note> and little ſport, To him I ſay, as the Angell ſaid to <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reue. 10.9.</note> 
               <hi>Take this little Booke, and eate it:</hi> Let thy Sauiors Diuine incarnation be thy deuout meditation: and be not afraid, or offended with the Latine quotations, for I haue made them for thy ſake, like Country-ſtiles, ſteppe ouer them, thou loſeſt not thy way by them, for their expoſitions follow them: and <hi>(ſi fortè mihi vitio detur)</hi> if I bee blamed for inſerting many marginall allegations, know that I did it for the more learneds ſake, that they might <hi>guſtare poſt fella fauos,</hi> the better relliſh their palates with taſting the hony of others Hiues.<note place="margin">Pro M. Caelio.</note> 
               <hi>Dandum eſt ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid aetati,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tullie</hi> of youth, ſo ſomething muſt be giuen to this learned age, ſomething to the ſolemnitie of the place, and ſomething to the expectation of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers. And indeed of this matter, all good pennes haue
<pb facs="tcp:16348:6"/> written, and tongues ſpoken, ſo that I haue gleaned but an handfull out of a plentifull harueſt: Yet though this ſubiect hath paſſed many worthy workemens hands, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (to my knowledge) I haue followed the methode of no particular authour. Thus haſt thou (ingenious Reader) the purpoſe of my publiſhing, and proceeding, and now ventrouſly I trafficke with this poore talent in this banke-route world, and intruſt thee with the benefite of my paines: let me not finde thee a bad debter, to repay me with enuie, inſtead of vſurie. <hi>Non quid ipſi poſſunt, ſed quid nos non poſſumus, dijudicant:</hi> An vſuall practiſe for loyterers to detract from others labours: for it is an eaſier taske to correct, then to compoſe to cenſure, then to write: <hi>But wiſedome is iuſtified of her Children,</hi> Matth. <hi>11.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mart. Epigr.</hi>
               </bibl> Carpere vel noli noſtra, velede tua.</q>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord, SAM. GAREY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16348:6"/>
            <head>A NEW-YEERS GIFT FOR THE SOVLE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GALATHIANS 4.4.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>4.</hi>
                     </bibl> But when the fulneſſe of Time was come, God ſent his Sonne, made of a woman, and made vnder the Law,</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>5.</hi>
                     </bibl> That he might redeeme them, which were vnder the Law that we might receiue the adoption of Sonnes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words doe containe two generall heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our Sauiors Incarnation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Mans Redemption.</p>
            <p>The time of this Incarnation ſet downe with a <hi>Quando,</hi> when, <hi>When the fulneſſe of Time was come:</hi> And the ſequell of the words deliuer three points.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Chriſts Diuinity:</item>
               <item>2. Chriſts humanity:</item>
               <item>3. Chriſts humility.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſts Diuinity, in theſe words, <hi>God ſent his Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſts humanity, in the next, <hi>Made of a woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſts humility, in the next, <hi>Made vnder the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:16348:7"/>
            <p>In Chriſts Diuinity, and humanity, I will conſider Chriſts two Natures,
<list>
                  <item>Diuine &amp;</item>
                  <item>Humane,</item>
               </list> confuting certaine hereſies from thence ariſing.</p>
            <p>In Chriſts humility I will obſerue <hi>his</hi> perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to worke our redemption, and reconciliation: And this<note n="a" place="margin">Polani part. Theol. lib. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>62.</hi>
               </note> Obedience hath two parts.
<list>
                  <item>2. <hi>impletio legis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>1. <hi>perſolutio poena</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The fulfilling of the law, ſet downe in our Text, made vnder the law, that is, as our Sauiour himſelfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it, Matth. 5.17. <hi>I came not to deſtroy the Law, but to fulfill it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The paiment of the puniſhment due for our ſinnes, is elſewhere ſet downe by the Apoſtle<note n="b" place="margin">Phil. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>Paul, Hee hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelfe, and became obedient vnto the death, euen the death of the Croſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond verſe declares the cauſe of Chriſts Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and humiliation, which was to redeeme them that were vnder the Law, and that<note n="c" place="margin">Piſcator ſuper Textum.</note> 
               <hi>Bifariam,</hi> two man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wayes.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>à maledictione legis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>à ceremonijs legis.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. From the curſe of the law, as<note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 3.13</note> 
               <hi>Paul, Chriſt hath redeemed vs from the curſe of the Law, being made a curſe for vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. From the ceremonies of the Law, as the<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 10.4</note> Apoſtle, <hi>Christ is the end of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Summe, or Corollary of all this, is propounded in the laſt words, <hi>That wee might receiue the adoption of Sonnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that by this you may perceiue, that all our ſpeech will generally hang vpon theſe foure words,
<q>Quando, Quis, Quomodo, Quare.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Quando,</hi> the time when, <hi>when the fulneſſe of time was come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Quis,</hi> who? <hi>God ſent his Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Quomodo,</hi> how? <hi>Made of a woman, made vnder the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16348:7"/>4. <hi>Quare,</hi> why, or wherefore? <hi>That He might redeeme them which were vnder the Law, that we might receiue the adoption of Sonnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe foure heads, as from the<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 2.10</note> foure diuided heads of Paradiſe, the weake ſtreames of our meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons flow.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the firſt, <hi>Quando,</hi> when, <hi>when the fulneſſe of time was come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The comming of Chriſt in the fleſh, is called <hi>the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time, for foure reſpects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. For the fulneſſe of Grace receiued by his<note n="g" place="margin">Iohn 1.16.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe <hi>Chriſt is the fulfilling of the</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.20</note> 
               <hi>promiſes of God, as being in him, yea, and Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe the<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 10.4</note> Law, and the<note n="k" place="margin">Luke 1.70</note> Prophets are fulfilled in him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe the times from Chriſts comming are the<note n="l" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.11</note> ends of the world, and it was fit he ſhould come ſo late, for two reaſons, as<note n="m" place="margin">Aquinas in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> alleadgeth them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe Chriſt is the Lord, and therefore meete there ſhould be long preparation, and expectation of ſo puiſſant a perſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe Chriſt is the graund<note n="n" place="margin">Math. 9.12</note> Phiſition of the world, and therefore requiſite, that all ſinners, his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, ſhould throughly feele their ſickeneſſe, before hee came to viſite, and redeeme them; <hi>venit de coelo magnus medicus, quia per totum vbi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iacebat agrotus,</hi> ſayth<note n="o" place="margin">Aug. ſuper Ioan.</note> 
               <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten,</hi> that is, The great Phyſicion came downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, becauſe euery where ſicke ſinners did lye and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh.</p>
            <p>And of this fulneſſe of Time <hi>(plenitudo, ſeu</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Piſcat. Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia ſuper locum.</note> 
               <hi>comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum temporis)</hi> the fulneſſe, and complement of all time, there were many prefiguring Typicall repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and propheticall predictions. All grounded vpon Gods firſt promiſe,<note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>Semen mulieris conteret caput ſenpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia:</hi> The ſeed of the woman ſhal break the Serpents head.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:16348:8"/>
            <p>This was the <hi>Axis,</hi> the Supporter, and foundation of all of them. Yea, God reiterated, and renewed his firſt promiſe to ſome of the Patriarkes.</p>
            <p>To<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 12.3.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham, In thee ſhall all the families of the earth be bleſſed:</hi> the ſame repromiſed to<note n="ſ" place="margin">Gen. 26.4.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaacke,</hi> repeated to<note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 28.14.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob,</hi> reeſtabliſhed to<note n="u" place="margin">2. Sam. 7.16.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid.</hi> And of this promiſed ſeed, who ſhould breake the Serpents head, the moſt ſignificatiue Type, was the Brazen Serpent, ſpoken of Numb. 21.8.9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſaack, Sampſon, Salomon, Ionas, Melchiſedeck,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, did beare a figure of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Not onely Types prefigured, but alſo many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies aymed at this fulneſſe of Time.</p>
            <p>The Patriarke<note n="x" place="margin">Gen. 49.10.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> lying vpon his death-bed, did propheſie of it vnto the Tribes of Iſrael, <hi>The Scepter ſhall not depart from Iudah, &amp;c. vntill Shilo come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Num. 24.17.</note>
               <hi>Balaam</hi> propheſied of this fulneſſe of Time, ſaying, <hi>There ſhall come a ſtarre of Iacob, and a Scepter ſhall riſe out of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> propheſieth of the comming, and kingdome of the Meſſias, yea his ſecond Pſalme ſpecially runnes vpon that matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salomon</hi> in his Canticles ſhadoweth forth Chriſts wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and welcome comming to his Spouſe the Church.</p>
            <p>The Prophet<note n="z" place="margin">Micah. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>Micah</hi> foretells the place of Chriſts Natiuity, <hi>Thou Bethleem Ephratah, art little to be among the thouſands of Iudah, yet out of thee ſhal be come forth, that ſhall be the ruler in Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Angell <hi>Gabriel</hi> foretold<note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 9.25.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet the fulneſſe of this time, when the Meſſias ſhould be borne.</p>
            <p>How liuely doth the Prophet<note n="*" place="margin">Eſay 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay</hi> deſcribe <hi>the fulnes of</hi> this <hi>Time</hi> with a demonſtratiue <hi>Ecce, Behold, a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine ſhall conceiue, and beare a Son, and yee ſhall call his name Emanuel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Harken, how the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ierem. 23, 5.</note> proclayms a freſh againe with another <hi>Ecce, Behold, the dayes come</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16348:8"/> the Lord) <hi>that I will raiſe vnto Dauid a righteous Branch, in his dayes Iudah ſhall bee ſaued, and Iſrael ſhall dwell ſafely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prophet:<note n="b" place="margin">Zechar. 9.9.</note> 
               <hi>Zechariah</hi> trebbles againe this <hi>Ecce, Behold, the King comes vnto you, be is iuſt, and ſaued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, poore, and riding vpon an Aſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prophet<note n="c" place="margin">Mala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Malachy</hi> (the laſt Eccho of all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets till <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt, ecchoes an <hi>Ecce</hi> too, <hi>Behold, I will ſend my meſſenger before me, and the Lord whom yee ſeeke, ſhall ſpeedily come to his Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus all the Prophets in ſenſe ſounded forth the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets verſe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <hi>Aggredere O magnos (aderit iam tempus) honores: chara deûm Soboles. — i.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O Son of God, thy labours great atchiue,</l>
               <l>The Time is come: vs from our ſins repriue.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Yea theſe holy men the Prophets, ſpake of this <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Time,</hi> as they were moued by the holy<note n="d" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.21.</note> Ghoſt, and as the Apoſtle<note n="e" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.10</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks, of which ſaluation the Prophets haue enquired, and ſearched, which propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the grace which ſhould come vnto you.</p>
            <p>Nay, the Prophets not onely looked, but longed for <hi>the fulneſſe of this Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How patheticall is<note n="f" place="margin">Eſay 64 1.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay</hi> in his deſirous expectation! <hi>Oh that thou wouldeſt breake the heauens, and come downe, and that the mountaines might melt at thy preſence!</hi> So that I may ſay, that Chriſt was not onely,<note n="g" place="margin">Apoc. 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>Agnus mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus: a Lamb ſlaine,</hi> but alſo, <hi>expectatus ab origine mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di: expected from the beginning of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the Types, they were repreſentatiue; al the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies ſignificatiue; but at this <hi>Quando, this, fulneſſe of Time,</hi> the Meſſias is exhibitatiue: they did repreſent, now hee preſents himſelfe.</p>
            <p>At which <hi>fulneſſe of Time</hi> all the Types were ended, all the propheſies of his birth fulfilled, yea all the heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Oracles ceaſed.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:16348:9"/>
               <l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iuvenal.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <hi>—ceſſant oracula Delphis. i.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Oracles which at Delphos ſpake,</l>
               <l>at his comming ceaſed, and brake.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Chriſts birth diſſolued thoſe deluſiue workes of the diuell: at his comming all mute, and marred.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Exceſſere omnes Adytis, artſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> relictis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dij quibus imperiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hoc ſteterat—i.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All fained gods the Altars leaue,</l>
               <l>To which the Empire once did cleaue.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Away, yee falſe Oracles of fained gods. Behold, the heauenly Oracle of <hi>Truth</hi> deſcends himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Vaniſh, yee darker Types, the ſhadowes of this ſunne, the Sonne of righteouſneſſe appeares himſelfe, and that in the ſigne <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeede the incredulous Iewes, and as<note n="h" place="margin">Acts 7.51</note> 
               <hi>Stephen</hi> brands with two ſtigmatical Epithites, <hi>Stiffe-necked,</hi> and <hi>Vncircumciſed;</hi> they ſtill expect the fulneſſe of this time, their <hi>Quando</hi> is not yet come.</p>
            <p>But we, whom God hath enlightened with the word of <hi>Truth,</hi> we knowe, and belieue, that <hi>the fulneſſe of Time is come,</hi> and at this time the newes of Chriſts actuall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity was proclaymed by the tongue of an<note n="i" place="margin">Luke 2.10.11</note> Angell, that <hi>vnto vs is borne this day in the City of Dauid a Sauiour, which is Chriſt the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh let vs celebrate, not annually, but perpetually, the memory of Chriſts<note n="*" place="margin">O Natiuitas honorabilis mundo, amabilis hominibus, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſtigabilis An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelis, in his om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus admirabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, &amp;c. Ber.</note> natiuity. <hi>Natiuitas Chriſti nata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Chriſtiani,</hi> that is, the Birth-day of Chriſt, is the birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day of euery Chriſtian,<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 118 24</note> 
               <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made,</hi> yea wherein the Lord was made, <hi>let vs be glad and reioyce in it:</hi> let vs powre out <hi>Eſayes</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay 49.13</hi> Coeli Regenato, Angelorie chori prodeunt, hymnli dicunt, &amp;c. Greg. lib. <hi>27.</hi> moral.</note> words, <hi>Reioyce, O heauens, and be ioyfull, O earth, burſt forth into prayſes, O mountaines; for God hath comforted his people; and will haue mercy vpon his afflicted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt, who was in the olde Teſtament <hi>velatus,</hi> ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed forth, is at <hi>this fulneſſe of Time, reuelatus,</hi> reuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and exhibited. Before, <hi>praedictus,</hi> foretold; now, <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatus,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:16348:9"/> preſent, preacht, and publiſht: as<note n="m" place="margin">Periſtep. hym. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Prudentius</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n his hymne.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mortale corpus ſumpſit immortalitas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vt dum caducum portat aeternus Deus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tranſire noſtrum poſſit ad coelestia,</hi> that is,</l>
               <l>Immortality takes mortality,</l>
               <l>That whileſt Eternity beares our frailty,</l>
               <l>We might paſſe vnto the Deity.</l>
            </q>
            <p>As<note n="n" place="margin">1. Tim. 3. the laſt.</note> 
               <hi>Paul: God is manifeſted in the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me in a word ſpeak ſomthing with celerity, which doth concerne the ſpirituall celebrity, and ſolemnity of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he fulneſſe of this Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I wil begin with borrowing S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Bernards</hi> words,<note n="o" place="margin">Ber. in Ser. de Aduent.</note> ſpeaking of the ſame point, <hi>Dignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt (fratres) vt tota de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otione domini celebremus Aduentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, delectati ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ſtupefacti ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta dignatione, infla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mati ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta dilectione, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. It is fit, <hi>Brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that we ſhould celebrate the Lords co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming with great deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, delighted with ſuch heauenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſolation, admiring at ſuch humiliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, rauiſhed with diuine loue, and affection. Saint<note n="p" place="margin">Ambroſe in Lucam.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> alſo ſpeaks of the ſame matter after the ſame manner, <hi>Hoc tempus non ſine cauſa Domini Aduentus vocatur: deo Sancti patres celebrare coeperunt Aduentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt vnuſquiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> praeparet fidelis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t dignè valeat celebrare: i.</hi> This time not without cauſe is called, The Lords co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, therfore the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers celebrated this comming, preparing themſelues faithfully, reforming themſelues dutifully, that they might worthily celebrate, and ſolemnize it.</p>
            <p>This is a time of ſpirituall feſtiuity, not of prophane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anity, dicing, dancing, carding, or carowſing; but of Chriſtian exultation, and ioyfull<note n="q" place="margin">Chriſtus ſit mel in ore, melos in aure, Iubilae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in corde.</note> Iubilation, <hi>ſpeaking to our ſelues in Pſalmes, and in ſpirituall ſongs, ſinging and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aking melody to the Lord in your hearts, Epheſ.</hi> 5.19.</p>
            <p>A time of piety, a time of pitty, and charity: the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>equires your heart; the ſecond your heart and hand. For the firſt, ſay with<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 108.1</note> 
               <hi>Dauid, O God my heart is prepared,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16348:10"/> ſo is my tongue, I will ſing, and giue prayſe.</hi> And for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, doe with<note n="ſ" place="margin">Iob. 31.17.</note> 
               <hi>Iob, I haue not eaten my morſels alone, the fatherleſſe haue eaten thereof.</hi> A fit time to extend the fulneſſe of mercy to others, ſince the fulneſſe of mercy at this time was extended to vs.<note n="*" place="margin">Solacharitas eſt, qua vincit omnia, &amp; ſine qua nihil valent omnia, &amp; vbi fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, trabit ad ſe omnia. Aug. de doctri. Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</note> Feede Chriſts poore mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers with the morſels of your bread, that Chriſt may ſay vnto you at his ſecond comming, <hi>I was hungry, and you gaue me bread,</hi> Math. 25.35.</p>
            <p>But alacke for pity, the proud back cruciates the poor belly; pride is the cut-throate of pitty and charity. As our Sauiour, <hi>Charity waxeth cold, but iniquity doth abound:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Non ſolùm a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarus eſt, qui ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit aliena, ſed ille auarus eſt, qui cupidè ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat ſua. Aug.</note> Charity is turned to brauerie, and prodigality; large houſes, but ſtraite gates; and the Porter Couetouſnes keepes out <hi>Lazarus</hi> from any entrance. In the better Times, this was a time of charitable deuotion, which is now turned to deuoration.</p>
            <p>The rich feaſt, and the poore faſt; they dine, theſe pine; they ſurfet, theſe ſtarue; yet both ſeruants to one Maſter. Oh you, whome God hath bleſſed with a plentifull ſtore,<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 11.1</note> 
               <hi>Caſt your bread vpon the waters, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many dayes ye ſhall finde it. Tanta est apud Deum hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalitatis gratia, vt ne potus aquae frigidae a praemijs remu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerationis immunis ſit,</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith<note n="u" place="margin">Ambroſ. de offic.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> 1. God is ſo regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of hoſpitality, and charity, that a cup of cold water lacks not a<note n="*" place="margin">Si vere tua ſunt, expende ad l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cra, &amp; pro ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renis coeleſtia commutato, Ber. Ser. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> reward. Doe the works of mercy, for God loues a cheerefull giuer.</p>
            <p>There are many Chriſtmaſſe-Non-reſidents, that run to the Citty, to liue in obſcurity; who ſhould liue in their Country, to keepe hoſpitality: an Epidemiall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, as common as the tooth-ake.<note n="*" place="margin">Auarus nec patientibus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patitur, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeris ſubuenit, ſed offédit Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, proximum, et ſeipſum. Deo detinet debita, proximo dene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat neceſſaria, &amp; ſihi ſubtrahit opportuna. Inn. de vilitate cond. humanae.</note> againſt whom, or to whom the poore cryes, as the Infants did to their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in the deſtruction of Ieruſalem, <hi>Lament.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Where is bread, and drinke?</hi> and finding none, giue vp the ghoſt in the mothers boſome. Oh you, whom God hath made well-ſtored Stewards (none are Treaſurers) open your-gates, and let the King of glory his pooreſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16348:10"/> members enter in: if you will not, remember<note n="*" place="margin">Ideo rogam Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, non exau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur in tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, quia rogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Lazarum non exaudiuit in terris, Aug. hom. de Diuite.</note> 
               <hi>Diues,</hi> he as a Gentleman, as many are, without Armes, or Heral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, and becauſe he ſhut his gate, <hi>patuit atri ianua Ditis,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e paſſed the broad-gates of hell: hee would not giue <hi>Lazarus, micam panis,</hi> a crum of bread; he could not get <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fterward, <hi>guttam aquae,</hi> a drop of water to coole his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ongue. Shew mercy, if yee expect mercy: be mercifull, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your heauenly Father is mercifull.<note n="*" place="margin">Foeneratur Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino, qui largi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur pauperi. <hi>Prou. 19.17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He that giues to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore, lends to the Lord,</hi> and his righteouſneſſe remaines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r euer.</p>
            <p>Prepare your ſelues, and ſoules with pietie, charity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>delity, humility, to welcome this <hi>fulneſſe of Time;</hi> put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your wedding garments, <hi>fidem perfectam, charitatem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmatam,</hi> a liuely faith, a louely charity. Behold, The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmortall King of mans redemption comes vnto you,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Virg.</hi>
                     </bibl> 
                     <hi>I am noua progenies calo dimittur alto:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A God-man is ſent from God to man.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Welcome him with all fidelity, humility, piety, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ordiall ſanctity and ſolemnitie. If a mortall King ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome vnto you, I knowe you would adorne your ſelues, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rouide a ſolemne preparation to entertaine him with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll duty and diligence. Lo, the greateſt King of all, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ompariſon of whome, all earthly Kings are <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tomi,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oates, and mites, <hi>in</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Reuel. 19 16.</note> 
               <hi>cuius foemore ſcriptum, Rex re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um, &amp;c.</hi> In whoſe thigh is written, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords. Behold, he comes vnto you, to lodge in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he houſes of your hearts by faith. <hi>Behold, I ſtand at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oore, and knocke; if any man heare my voice, and open the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oore, I will come in vnto him, and will ſup with him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e with me,</hi> Apoc. 3.20.</p>
            <p>Be thankfull to our Lord for <hi>the fulneſſe of this Time;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e dutiful to ſerue him at al times. And to end this point with the Pſalmiſts<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 149.1.2</hi> Licèt Deus cunctes dies cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auerit, ſingulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tamen hunc Diem feciſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur, qui Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni natiuitate ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratus est, in quo exultari conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit et latari, &amp;c Caſſ. in Pſ. <hi>11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> ſong, <hi>Sing ye vnto the Lord a new ſong, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t his praiſe be heard in the Congregation of Saints: let Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael reioyce in him that made him, and let the children of Sion reioyce in their King.</hi> And thus much, or rather thus
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16348:11"/> little of the firſt point, <hi>the Time, Quando, when the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Time was come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next part I am to touch, is <hi>Quis,</hi> who? <hi>God ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> his Sonne,</hi> the <hi>Card<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Baſis</hi> of <hi>this Time,</hi> and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>God ſent his Sonne:</hi> wherein I will obſerue three things. Firſt, the inſeparable working of the Trinity in the work of mans redemption. Secondly, the confutation of the hereſie of<note n="c" place="margin">Vide Vrſin. doct. Chriſt. <hi>2.</hi> par. tit. de dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Chriſti. Noetus, et Pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas hanc haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin tenebant: vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Aug. haereſ. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sabellius,</hi> who did maintaine the Son to be, <hi>Eaudem perſonam cum patre, &amp; Spiritu ſancto,</hi> that is, the ſame perſon with the Father, and the holy Spirit, when wee ſee here, that they be diſtinct, <hi>God ſent his Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The manifeſtation of the hereſie of<note n="d" place="margin">Aug. haereſ. <hi>45.</hi> De hac haereſi vide Zanchium &amp; Theophilact. in Philip. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Photinus,</hi> who denied the diuine nature of Chriſt, affirmed here, <hi>God ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> his Sonne,</hi> that is his naturall Son, begotten from eternity.</p>
            <p>For the firſt: The workes of the Trinity be inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and indiuiſible: for as the Trinity were Agents, in the creation of man, <hi>Faciamus hominem,</hi> Let vs make man, Gen. 1.26. ſo Actors at the Redemption of man.</p>
            <p>In this high and heauenly worke there concurred the wiſdome of the Almighty Father, the willingneſſe of the All-mercifull Sonne, the power of the All-ſanctifying Spirit; the Father willed, the Sonne worked, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt bleſſed; the Father decreed, the Sonne perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally performed, and the holy Ghoſt ſanctifyed the worke of redemption: in one word, <hi>God ſent his Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Vide Muſc. loc. com. tit. de Incar. verb.</note>Diuines, to expreſſe this myſtery, vſe this ſimilitude, imagining three virgins weauing of a coate, and one to weare it: ſo the three perſons of the holy Trinity wrought in the Incarnation of the Word, but the Sonne alone did put on the fleſh: for it was conuenient, that He that was Sonne in the God-head, ſhould be Sonne in manhood.</p>
            <p>Now, as the Creation of all is attributed to God the Father, in reſpect of the matter; to God the Sonne, in reſpect of the diſpoſition of the forme; and to God the holy Ghoſt, in regard of the preſeruation of both: So
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16348:11"/> the Redemption is attributed to the Father. <hi>Pater per fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> taenquam fons,</hi> as the learned<note n="f" place="margin">Vrſin. doct. Chriſt. <hi>2.</hi> par. tit. redemp. p. <hi>34. 5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vrſinus:</hi> the Father by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Sonne, as the fountaine: it is attributed and aſcribed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Sonne, who effected it, <hi>merito, &amp; ſua perſona:</hi> by his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erits, perſon and paſſion. It is attributed to the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Tanquam immediatè effector regenerationis,</hi> as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ediatly the effector of regeneration: yea, as that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y <hi>Vrſinus</hi> ſaith again,<note place="margin">Eodem loco.</note> 
               <hi>Efficacia eſt communis Tribus perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is, modus autem eſt filio proprius,</hi> that is, the efficacy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on to the Trinity, the manner is ſolely proper to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onne.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You may perceiue that fond, and forlorne hereſie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f<note n="*" place="margin">Vide Calu. harm. in Ioh. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; Vrſin. doct. Chriſt <hi>2.</hi> par. pag. <hi>378.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sabellius,</hi> who denied Chriſt to bee a diſtinct perſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om the Father and the holy Spirit, affirmed here, <hi>God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent his Sonne, Alius perſonaliter, non aliud eſſentialiter;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nother perſonally, though not another eſſentially, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Auſten: filius ex ipſo, cum ipſo, hoc quod ipſe:</hi> i.<note n="g" place="margin">Aug. de Ciu. dei. lib. <hi>11.</hi> ca. <hi>10</hi> &amp; Lomb. <hi>1.</hi> ſent. diſt. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> The Sonne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f himſelfe, with himſelfe, the ſame which himſelfe, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he foreſaid S.<note n="h" place="margin">Auguſt. ſer. <hi>4</hi> de temp.</note> 
               <hi>Auſten</hi> ſpeakes.</p>
            <p>We know and beleeue the Vnity of the Godhead, yet a<note n="*" place="margin">In ſumma Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate tantum eſt vna, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum tres ſimul ſunt, ita ſingula ſunt in ſingulis, &amp; ſingula in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, &amp; omnia in omnibus, &amp; vnum omnia? Aug. lib. <hi>6.</hi> de Trinitat.</note> Trinity of perſons, God in eſſence one; in perſons three<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet an Vnity in Trinity, and a Trinity in Vnity, all Co-equall, Co-eſſentiall, Co-eternall: yet all diſtinct, the Father from the Sonne, the Sonne from the Father, and the holy Ghoſt from both.</p>
            <p>I might here meet with the hereſies of <hi>Arrius, Paulus Samoſatenus, Seruetius,</hi> and others, who maintaine, that the Sonne is not equall to the Father: but the Apoſtle<note n="i." place="margin">Phil. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> hath condemned this error, ſaying, <hi>Chriſt being in the forme of God, thought it no robbery to be equal with God:</hi> yea, it is an orthodoxe Axiome of truth and beliefe, that<note n="*" place="margin">Vrſin. doct. Chriſt. <hi>2.</hi> par. pag. <hi>381.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>eſt patri equalis &amp; conſubſtantialis:</hi> i. the Word is equall to the Father, and conſubſtantiall: true it is, that <hi>alius pater, alius filius eſt:</hi> the Father is one, and the Sonne another: But how? <hi>Non alius Deus pater, nec alius Deus filius, nec alius Deus Spiritus ſanctus; hi enim Tres vnum
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16348:12"/> ſunt,</hi> as writes<note n="k" place="margin">Vrſin. doct. Chriſt. pag. <hi>382.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vrſinus,</hi> that is. The Father is not another God, or the Sonne another God, or the holy Ghoſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother God, for theſe three be one.</p>
            <p>The Father is firſt, not in priority of Nature, Honor or Time, but<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Perkins</hi> vpon the Creed.</note> Order: or as the Scholemen, <hi>Prioritate origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> in priority of beginning. <hi>Pater eſt principium non de principio, Filius principium a principio,</hi> ſaith<note n="m" place="margin">Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. <hi>1.</hi> part. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. quaeſt. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3</hi> art. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thomas:</hi> that is, The Father is beginning, not of beginning; the Sonne beginning from beginning: <hi>In principio erat, hoc eſt, a principio erat,</hi> ſaith<note n="n" place="margin">Theophil. enarrat. in <hi>1.</hi> Ioh. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theophilact;</hi> that is, In the beginning was the Word, that is, from beginning. Or as <hi>Auſten, Principium principio carens:</hi> that is, A be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, wanting beginning: Or as<note n="o" place="margin">Caluin. har. in <hi>1.</hi> Ioh. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Caluin, Principi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um omni tempore ſuperius,</hi> a beginning before all time: indeed (as a<note n="p" place="margin">Aug. de Trin. lib. <hi>4</hi> cap. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> Father writes) <hi>Pater eſt totius Diuinitatis, vel Deitatis principium,</hi> that is, The Father is the eternal beginning of the Deity: and as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Creed, The Father is of none, the Sonne is of the Father alone, and the holy Ghoſt of Both. <hi>Filius per aeternam generatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ſpiritus per aeternam proceſſionem,</hi> ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">Piſcat. in Ioh. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Piſcator:</hi> i. The Son by an eternall generation, the holy Ghoſt by an eternall proceſſion. I will conclude this myſtery with<note n="q" place="margin">Ber. de conſid. ad Eugen. lib. <hi>5.</hi> Vbi quaritur v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas trinitatis, nec periculoſius alicubi erratur, nec aliquid la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borioſius quaeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, nec fructuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius aliquid inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitur, &amp;c. Aug. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Trinit.</note> 
               <hi>Bernards</hi> words, <hi>Scrutari temeritas, credere pietas, noſſe vita eſt:</hi> i. Too ſubtilly to explore it, is temerity, to adore it ſimply, is true piety, to know it fully, brings eternitie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Behold that exploded hereſie of <hi>Photinus,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the diuine Nature of Chriſt, acknowledging him perfect man, but not God, which diuine nature is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, <hi>God ſent his Sonne,</hi> that is, <hi>filium ex eſſentia Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris genitum,</hi> i. the Sonne begotten of the Eſſence of his Father: and it is a diuine rule among<note n="*" place="margin">Vrſin. s <hi>2.</hi> part. pag. <hi>382.</hi>
               </note> Diuines, that, <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia diuina nec diuidi, nec multiplicari, nec alia creari po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt:</hi> i. The diuine Eſſence cannot be diuided, multiplied, or another created; therefore perfect God in reſpect of his diuine nature: and this confutes <hi>Ebion,</hi> and <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> two hereticks, that denied that Chriſt was not true God,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16348:12"/> before he aſſumed fleſh, which alſo the Euangeliſt <hi>Iohn</hi> more at large declares, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. <hi>The word was made fleſh,</hi> and that this word was God before, he ſhewes in the 1. verſe of all, <hi>And that Word was God: ſi Sermo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, ergo aeternus Deus</hi> (ſaith<note n="r" place="margin">Caluin. harm. in cum locum.</note> 
               <hi>Caluin</hi>) If the word was God, therefore God from euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>Now you are to know, that the<note n="*" place="margin">Perſona Chriſti vna eſt, quia v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt Chriſtus: Polan. part. lib. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>57.</hi>
               </note> perſon of Chriſt is one; for but one Chriſt: his natures two, as I mentioned in the beginning,
<list>
                  <item>Diuine and</item>
                  <item>Humane:</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Diuine, expreſſed here, <hi>God ſent his Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humane, which followes, <hi>Factus ex muliere:</hi> Made of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> woman.</p>
            <p>And there is not one point in all our faith, ſo inuolued with ſo many hereſies, as is this point of our beliefe, of Chriſts Diuinity and Humanity.</p>
            <p>It<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide Muſc. loc. com. tit. de incarn. verb. de hac re.</note> was the policy, and marueilous ſleight of Satan, to entrench the faith of the faithfull, with bulwarkes of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies fronted on euery ſide.</p>
            <p>The<note n="*" place="margin">Arrius filium creaturam, &amp; facturam Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris eſſe tenet: Vide Theophil. enar. in Joh. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> Vide eundem Theoph. eodem loco, de his haereſ. dicentem.</note> 
               <hi>Arrians</hi> deny Chriſt to be perfect God, of equal ſubſtance with the Father.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Marcionites</hi> deny Chriſt to haue been borne in the fleſh, or perfect man.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Manichees</hi> confeſſe his diuine nature, but not hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Photinia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> attribute humane nature but not diuine.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Neſtorians</hi> grant two natures to be in Chriſt, but ſo, that they make two perſons, and ſo cut one Chriſt in two, one as the Sonne of God, one as the Sonne of man.</p>
            <p>The<note n="*" place="margin">Vide Bellar. de Chriſto. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Euticheans</hi> affirme one perſon to be in Chriſt, and but one nature, namely, the diuine, ſaying, that the humane nature was ſwallowed vp by the coniunction of the Word: thus,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Incidet in Scyllam, qui vult vitare Charibdin:</hi> that is,</l>
                  <l>He ſhall fall vpon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ocks,</l>
                  <l>that would eſcape the ſands.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:16348:13"/> Our beliefe, like<note n="ſ" place="margin">Matth. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> ſhip, is toſſed with Satans winds, and waues,
<q>—vnda ſuperaduenit vndae:</q> one waue of error followes another, like <hi>Iobs</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iob 1.</note> meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in the necke of another, that vnleſſe we be godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to put a difference twixt perſon and nature; it wil be perillous to ſcape the rocks, and eaſily catch in theſe <hi>Meanders</hi> and Labirinths of Satan.</p>
            <p>And herein to call to your remembrance one princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of your faith: you are to know, that there is one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of one ſelfe ſame Chriſt: Yet two Natures<note n="*" place="margin">In perſonali vnione diſtinctae manent, &amp; inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſae naturae, ſiue proprietates, ſiue eſſentiam, ſiue operationes ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ſpectes, Polan. part. l. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>59.</hi>
               </note> diſtinct; <hi>inconfuſae,</hi> not confounded, and yet a perſonall vnion of both Natures, not one diſſeuered from another: That of God, which is of the Word, which tooke vpon him fleſh; and that of man, which is of the fleſh, that was aſſumed, of which none is changed into the other, but each of them doe keepe their proper and naturall condition, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in reſpect of the eſſence, proprieties, or operations of them.</p>
            <p>So that there is a threefold plenitude in our Redeemer Chriſt Ieſus: 1. <hi>Verus Deus,</hi> true God. 2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erus homo,</hi> true man. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i.</hi> God and man, by a perſonall vnion: the which three are equipollent to thoſe three wonderfull workes of the omnipotent Maieſty in the Aſſumption of the fleſh: and as S.<note n="u" place="margin">Bern. ſer. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> ſtiles them, <hi>Mirabiliter ſingularia, &amp; ſingulariter mirabilia,</hi> i. mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly ſingular, and ſingularly miraculous. What bee they?</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Coniunction of both Natures. <hi>Deus &amp; homo,</hi> i. God and man. Secondly, <hi>Mater &amp; virgo,</hi> that is, <hi>Marie</hi> his mother, and yet a Virgin. Thirdly <hi>fides, &amp; cor humanum,</hi> i. faith, and mans heart vnited by beleeuing it. And ſurely, the firſt three are as equally wonderfull: firſt, true God: ſecondly, true man: thirdly, God and man. As God, <hi>plenus gloria,</hi> full of glory: as man, <hi>plenus obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia,</hi> full of obedience: as God and man <hi>plenus gratia,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:16348:13"/> full of grace. I meane, <hi>gratia</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">See the Biſh. of Ely his Sermon, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched on Eaſter day. 1614. p. 19.</note> 
               <hi>vnionis:</hi> the grace of vnion: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or other grace in Chriſt, I take, that Diuines know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one.</p>
            <p>Now concerning Chriſts diuine nature, propounded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere, <hi>God ſent his Sonne,</hi> I ſhall not need to ſpend much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime: none but Atheiſts or hereticks deny it. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure: which is the mouth of God, and Oracle of truth, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery where teſtifie the verity of Chriſts Deity and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inity.</p>
            <p>So<note n="*" place="margin">Col. 1.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> to the Coloſſians ſaith, <hi>That Chriſt is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mage of the inuiſible God, the firſt begotten of all creatures: For by him were all things made in heauen, or earth, viſible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd inuiſible, Angels, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So<note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 16.16.</note> 
               <hi>Peter, Thou art Chriſt, the Sonne of the liuing God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So<note n="y" place="margin">Pſalm. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid, Thou art my Sonne, this day haue I begotten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So<note n="z" place="margin">Iohn 20.28.</note> 
               <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaith to Chriſt, <hi>My Lord, and my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 9.5.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> calles Chriſt, <hi>God ouer all, bleſſed for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So our<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 5.23.</note> Sauiour ſaith of himſelfe, that <hi>all men ſhould honour the Sonne, as they honour the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So<note n="b" place="margin">Col. 2.9. Iohn 5.19. 1. Iohn 1.2.20. Iohn 16.15. Iohn 5.26. Matth. 28.18. Phil. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of Chriſt, that <hi>in him dwelleth all the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the God-head bodily:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, innumerable teſtimonies of Scripture to auerre the ſame.</p>
            <p>The Scripture aſcribes the ſame diuine proprieties to the Sonne, which be attributed to the Father: that he is, <hi>omnipotens, omnipraeſens, omniſciens,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, omnipotent, omnipreſent, all-knowing, the knower of the ſecrets of the heart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16.</p>
            <p>Yea, to conclude this, with the words of the<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 1.2.3.</note> Author to the Hebrewes, ſpeaking of Chriſt, <hi>That he is the heyre of all things, by whom God made the world, the brightneſſe of the glory, and the ingraued forme of his perſon, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp all things by his mighty word, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:16348:14"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Prudentius in Pſychomachia.</note> 
                  <hi>Ille manet, quod ſemper erat, quod non erat, eſſe incipiens.</hi> —</l>
               <l>He that was euer an eternall God, in mans nature tooke a beginning.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>By theſe teſtimonies are confuted diuers hereticks:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Zanchius in Phil. <hi>2.5.</hi>
               </note>1. <hi>Ebion, Cerinthus, Photinus, Paulus Samoſatenus,</hi> holding that Chriſt had no being, before hee tooke on him the ſhape of man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sophronius,</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">Caluin. harm. in Ioh. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Seruetus,</hi> imagining that the Word was not actually, and really ſubſiſting from eternity, <hi>non fuiſſe rem verè ſubſiſtentem, ſed decretum tantummodò in mente Dei de hoc homine creando, &amp; ſua deitate implendo:</hi> Not to be a ſubſtance truly ſubſiſting, but only a decree of God of creating this man, and fulfilling him by his Deity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Carpocrates</hi> and <hi>Arrius,</hi> acknowledging that Chriſt had another nature beſides his humane, but not of the ſame ſubſtance with the Father.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note n="*" place="margin">Bellarm. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Chriſto.</note> 
               <hi>Philoponus, Valentin, Gentilis,</hi> and other <hi>Tritheiſts</hi> impiouſly maintaining that the three perſons are three Gods eſſentially differing in number, and nature; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Catholicke faith acknowledges with <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Creed, that the God-head of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghoſt is all one, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus Chriſt being true God, tooke on him the ſhape of<note n="*" place="margin">Homo factus, naturam ſuſcipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo noſtram, non amittendo ſuam, Aug. epiſt. <hi>120.</hi> cap. <hi>36.</hi> Ruffinus in ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol.</note> man, not by confuſion of Subſtance, but by perſonall Vnion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God ſent his Sonne,</hi> not adopted Sonne, as all the elect are by grace; not Sonne by creation, as the Angels, and <hi>Adam</hi> was before his fall; but his naturall Sonne, be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from eternity: called Gods onely begotten Sonne: <hi>So God loued the world, that he gaue his only</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ocatur vnige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus, qui ante humanam natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram existebat, &amp;c. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin. doct. Chri. pag. <hi>373.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>begotten Son, &amp;c. Ioh.</hi> 3.16. Equall to the Father, as touching his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head: for <hi>whatſoeuer things the Father doth, the ſame things doth the Sonne alſo, Ioh.</hi> 5.19. For he is of the ſame nature, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Greeke Writers, of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16348:14"/> ſame, not of the like nature; Gods naturall Sonne, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aturally God, of the ſame eſſence with his Father. <hi>Qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lius Dei naturalis eſt, habet eaudem integram, &amp; imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elem Dei eſſentiam communicatam,</hi> ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin. doct. Ch. <hi>2.</hi> par. pag. <hi>382.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vrſinus,</hi> that is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee that is the naturall Sonne of God, hath the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>otall, and impartible eſſence of God communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that, damnable, and deteſtable is the hereſie of <hi>Photinus, Ebion, Cerinthus, &amp;c.</hi> infringing Chriſts God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, whoſe diuinity is here expreſſed, <hi>God ſent his Sonne:</hi> here is the <hi>Quis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next followeth, <hi>Quomodo:</hi> how or in what manner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee was ſent? <hi>Factus ex muliere: Made of a woman:</hi> if made of a woman, then Hee was perfect man; which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erthrowes the hereſie of the <hi>Marcionites,</hi> yea, all ſuch as deny Chriſt to bee perfect man, or to be come in the fleſh Saint<note n="g" place="margin">2. Ioh. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> brands them with a character of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt, ſaying, <hi>Many deceiuers are entred into the world, which confeſſe not, that Ieſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh: hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat is ſuch an one, is a deceiuer, and an Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made of a woman;</hi> he doth not ſay, <hi>genitus ex muliers,</hi> that is, begotten of a woman:<note place="margin">Eraſm. annot. in Textum.</note> for though Chriſt had the materials of his body from <hi>Mary,</hi> yet the holy Ghoſt was agent in his wonderfull conception.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ex muliere, non in muliere,</hi> of a woman, not in a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, as <hi>Gorranus,</hi> and <hi>Aquinas</hi> vpon this place, which confutes<note n="h" place="margin">Aug. haer. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Valentinus</hi> hereſie, who taught, that Chriſt had not his body from the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> but brought it down from heauen, &amp; paſſed thorow the wombe of the Virgin, as water thorow a conduit pipe: contrary to the text here, <hi>Made of a woman:</hi> and the Prepoſition<note n="i" place="margin">Aquinas in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> 
               <hi>ex,</hi> notes the matter, as an houſe is made of ſtones and tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, &amp;c. So<note n="k" place="margin">Luke 1.42.</note> 
               <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſpeaks to <hi>Mary, Bleſſed is the fruit of thy wombe.</hi> So<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 9.5.</hi> Pecerit filium mater, a quo ipſa nutriretur, poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſqua nutriret, &amp;c. Aug. ſer <hi>6.</hi> de nat. domi,</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the Iſraelites, ſaith, <hi>Of whom are the Fathers, and of whom Chriſt, concerning the fleſh came, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:16348:15"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Quid nobilius Dei Matre? quid caſtius? qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> corpus ſine corporis conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione generauit? &amp;c. Ambro. de virt. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Si quis ſanctam Mariam Dei param non credit, extra diuinitatem eſt. Si quis Chriſtum per Virginem, tanquam per canalem fluxiſſe, non autem in ea, diuino modo, quia abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> viri opera, humano, quia iuxt a pariendi conſuetudinem, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum eſſe dixerit, aequè Atheus eſt,</hi> ſaith<note n="m" place="margin">Nazian. Orat. <hi>51.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nazianen:</hi> or as<note n="n" place="margin">Chryſoſt. hom. in Pſal. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome, Maria dei filium concepit, credens verbo: hoc verbum caro factum eſt, &amp;c.</hi> that is, The Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> did conceiue the Son of God, beleeuing the Word, and this Word was made fleſh, how? as<note n="o" place="margin">Aug. hom. <hi>2.</hi> de Natiuit. Chriſti.</note> 
               <hi>Auſten</hi> ſpeakes of the ſame words, <hi>non depoſita, ſed ſepoſita Maieſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame<note n="p" place="margin">Aug. Ser. <hi>6.</hi> in Nat. Domi. Vnigenitus Dei exiſtens an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſecula, ex Maria vtero natus eſt homo, Gregor. Carnem induit verbii Deus ex Sancta Virgine, &amp;c. Epiph. contra Collyridianos, baer. <hi>79.</hi>
               </note> Father of this point, as in all other, excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, <hi>Peperit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgo filium, qui Deo filios faceret, &amp;c. Portanit in vtero filium mater, et hunc fudit in forma ſerui in terris, quem habent Angeli imperatorem in coelis,</hi> that is, The Virgin brought foorth a Sonne, who ſhould make ſonnes to GOD; the mother carries the Sonne in her wombe, and is borne in the ſhape of a ſeruant on earth, whom the Angels haue as their Emperour, or ruler in heauen.</p>
            <p>So that <hi>Valentinus</hi> was vaine, and much deceiued, in dreaming that Chriſt had not his body from the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> when our Text ſaith, <hi>He was made of a woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which <hi>Quomodo,</hi> how? you may behold great; nay, vnſpeakeable humiliation, that He, who is the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of heauen and earth, and to vſe Saint<note n="q" place="margin">Aug. Ser. <hi>27.</hi> de temp.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtens</hi> words, <hi>Factor terrae, factus in terra, &amp; exterra,</hi> that is, the Maker of the earth, made of earth: that Hee, who was the Father of <hi>Mary,</hi> ſhould be the child of <hi>Mary. Sine</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Aug. Ser. <hi>16.</hi> de temp.</note> 
               <hi>quo pater nunquam fuit, ſine quo mater nunquam fuiſſet:</hi> that is, without whom the Father neuer was, without whom the mother neuer had beene. This is ſuch a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that I may burſt forth in<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ier. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>Ieremies</hi> admiration, <hi>Obſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſcite coeli, ſuper hoc,</hi> that is, <hi>O yee heauens, be aſtonied at this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this ineffable, and admirable humiliation of Chriſt (as <hi>Polanus</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Polan. part. lib. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>58.</hi>
               </note> parts it) is diuided into two branches.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:16348:15"/>
               <item>1. The Incarnation: <hi>Made of a woman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The perfection of his obedience, <hi>Made vnder the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aw.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And the Incarnation of Chriſt hath three parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. His conception; <hi>Conceiued of the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vide Pola. part. ſup. dicto loco.</note>
               </item>
               <item>2. The perſonall vnion of both natures.</item>
               <item>3. The natiuity; I will but euen mention them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our memories.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Conceiued of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> It is an Article of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith: declared by the tongue of an<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke 1.35.</hi> Fides matris, non libido còn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceperat, Aug en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chirid. cap. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> Angell, that is, <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oly Ghoſt ſhal come vpon thee, and the power of the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igh ſhall ouerſhadow thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as workes of power are aſcribed to the Father, workes of wiſdome to the Sonne, and workes of loue to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he holy Ghoſt: ſo this being a worke of higheſt loue, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpecially aſcribed to the holy<note n="*" place="margin">Maldonat. in <hi>1.</hi> Matth.</note> Spirit.</p>
            <p>And this Article confutes three ſorts of hereticks: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irſt, the<note n="x" place="margin">Iraen. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cerinthians:</hi> ſecondly, the<note n="y" place="margin">Clem. Rom. inſtit. lib. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ebionites:</hi> thirdly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<note n="z" place="margin">Iraen lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi> Fecit grauidam Virginem ipſe, qui erat naſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus ex <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgine, &amp;c. Aug ſer. <hi>6.</hi> in Nat. Domi.</note> 
               <hi>Carpocratian</hi> hereticks, who all held, and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, that Chriſt was the naturall Sonne of <hi>Ioſeph, Verus, &amp; merus homo,</hi> that is, a meere naturall man, begotten of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſeph,</hi> contrary to the expreſſe Text, <hi>Ioſeph knew her not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill ſhe had brought forth her firſt borne Sonne,</hi> Mat. 1. the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt verſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The perſonall vnion of both Natures. I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lude with two teſtimonies of diuine Scripture: firſt, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn; The Word was made fleſh:</hi> And as<note n="a" place="margin">Muſc. loc. com. tit. de verb. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carn.</note> 
               <hi>Muſculus</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ightly comments vpon thoſe words: <hi>There was made in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he wombe of the Virgin a coniunction of the Word and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leſh, that is to ſay, of the nature of God and man:</hi> there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he perſonall Vnion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond place out of<note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim. 3. the laſt.</note> 
               <hi>Timothy, God is manifeſted in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he fleſh;</hi> the which words the learned<note n="c" place="margin">Piſcat. ſuper cum locum.</note> 
               <hi>Piſcator</hi> para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hraſes thus, <hi>Filius natura ſua diuina inuiſibilis, effecit ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſibilem, aſſumpta vera natura humana in vnitatem ſua <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſonae,</hi> that is, the Son of God in his diuine nature inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16348:16"/> made him viſible, in aſſuming our humane nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vnion of his perſon. In a word, with<note n="d" place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine, Homo Deo acceſſit, non Deus à ſe receſſit;</hi> Our Lord tooke vpon him that which he was not, and left not to bee that which he was.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Natiuity, the manner of his Birth; I ſhall ſpeak of that afterward, as God ſhall aſſiſt, and the time permi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And in this Incarnation of Chriſt and the perſonall vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both Natures, we may behold his moſt incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and incomprehenſible compaſſion and affection to mankind, which I can better admire with ſilence, then expreſſe with vtterance.</p>
            <p>Oh beloued, had I ſides of braſſe, that could not bee wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, or an An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>els tongue to ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke with II, I ſhould fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhort in ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ng the bottome of this bottomleſſe and boundleſſe compaſſion.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non mihi ſi centum voces, linguae quoque centum ſufficerent, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>An hundred tongues and voicEs were not able,</l>
               <l>To ſhew Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loue herein proportionable.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Our Lord, and Sauiour did ſo <hi>ſitire noſtram ſalutem,</hi> ſo ardently thirſt after our ſaluation, that hee did vouchſafe to be borne of a woman. <hi>Lambit vbera, qui regit ſidera, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet qui verbum eſt,</hi> as<note n="e" place="margin">Aug. ſer. <hi>5.</hi> de temp.</note> 
               <hi>Auſten,</hi> that is, He ſucks the breſts, that rules the Starres; he is an Infant, and cannot ſpeake, and yet he is the Word: great humility, to aſſume our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity; made of a woman, and made<note n="f" place="margin">Iohn 1.14.</note> fleſh, and found in ſhape as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Phi.</hi> 2.7. He did not take Angelical nature, and as the<note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 2.16.</note> Author to the Hebrews: <hi>He in no ſort took the Angels, but he took the ſeed of Abraham: Vt nos aequaret An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelis, minoratus eſt ab Angelis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Anſelmus:</hi> that is, That he might make vs equall to the Angels, he made himſelf lower then the Angels. So that there is greater affinity twixt God and man, then twixt God and the Angels; for he aſſumed our nature, and was made of a woman. Wee doe not reade in any place of Scripture, that Chriſt did
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16348:16"/> euer call the Angels <hi>fratres ſuos,</hi> that is, his brethren, as he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lles men.<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 22.22. Heb. 2.12.</hi> Magna dignitas eſt fideliu, quod nominantur filij Dei, &amp; fratres filij Dei V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ti, &amp;c. Piſcat. Analiſ. in Haebreos. c. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>10.11.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Narrabo nomen tuum fratribus meis,</hi> that is, will declare thy name vnto my brethren. I may heere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y vſe the words of a Father. <hi>Maritari noluit verbum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t altiùs nubere non potuit caroglorioſiùs,</hi> that is, The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l God would marry no higher then our nature, our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ture could neu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r marry more gloriouſly.</p>
            <p>There is a three-fold affinity; firſt, legall by adoption. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, ſpirituall by regeneration. Thirdly, naturall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> generation. We are Gods adopted Sonnes by Ieſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1 5. Gods ſpirituall Sonne, by regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Except a man be borne again of water, and of the Spirit, cannot enter into the kingdome of God, Iohn</hi> 3.5. Indeed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e are not Gods naturall Sonnes, and yet Chriſt tooke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r nature vpon him; for there is but one Sonne of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r nature, &amp; that is Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Iohn 3.16. Math. 1.2.</note> called Gods only Begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Sonne in reſpect of his Father and diuine nature; firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>egotten in reſpect of his mother, and humane nature. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God the Father, called<note n="i" place="margin">Prudentius, Hym. de Eulalia Virgine. Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>andus ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nab. diuinorum, lib. <hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>48 § 2.</hi> Vide Ruffin. in Symbol.</note> 
               <hi>Omnipater,</hi> that is, the All-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er of all men, and all things, by creation, generally:</p>
            <p>Of good men, by adoption, ſpecially:</p>
            <p>Of Chriſt, by nature, ſingularly:</p>
            <p>We are only ſonnes by fauor, by adoption, by grace, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at not by nature. Oh, what an immeaſurable meaſure of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue was this, that He, who was Gods Son by nature, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> naturally God, of the ſame eſſence with the Father, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d receiuing al which the Father hath, ſauing the perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll propriety; who was ſo great, did make himſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> little, to make vs great, as<note n="k" place="margin">Tertull. lib. <hi>2.</hi> con. Marc.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me the Son of man; that we might be the<note n="l" place="margin">Cyp. ſer. de cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſyna. Vide, homo, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo alle amauit te, qui fecit te, vt propter te, factus ipſe, Hugo.</note> Sonnes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od: wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being very God, became very man, that hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight reconcile God to man, and man to God; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g ſo great, that the heauens cannot con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aine him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould make himſelfe ſo little, as to be contained in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ombe of a Virg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n. <hi>Filius Dei, qui fecit nos, factus eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r nos,</hi> as <hi>Auſten:</hi> that is, the Son of God, that made vs, to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16348:17"/> be made like vs. A mercy, or rather a myſtery ſo great, that I may ſay with<note n="m" place="margin">Eſay 66.8. Pſalm. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay, Who hath heard ſuch a thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> who hath ſeene ſuch things? That hee, who was the Lord of heauen and earth, ſhould become a ſeruant on earth, a ſeruant to men:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Optimam digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis viam o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendit dominus, nempe humilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, Baſ. in hex.</note> Nay (as <hi>Tertullian) nullificamen populi,</hi> that is, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as the outcaſt of men, a worme, and no man, the ſcorne of men, and the contempt of the people: <hi>Pſalme</hi> 22.6. it is ſuch a wonder, as ſince the heauens were made, there is none to paralell it.</p>
            <p>Rightly did the Prophet<note n="n" place="margin">Eſay 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay</hi> foretel his natiuity and name, ſtiling him <hi>Wonderfull:</hi> for he was wonderfull in his Conception, wonderfull in his Incarnation.</p>
            <p>The Scripture teacheth vs, how man comes foure waies into the world.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the helpe of man and woman, as all are vſually borne, <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Without any man and woman: ſo <hi>Adam</hi> was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of a man without a woman: ſo <hi>Eue</hi> was created, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.22.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Of a woman without a man, ſo Chriſt was borne, Matth. 1.18.</p>
            <p>Wonderfull Incarnation, that I may ſay with<note n="o" place="margin">Eſay 53.8.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay, Who can declare his generation? Secundum conditionem na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae natus ex foemina, ſuper conditionem naturae natus ex <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgine,</hi> ſaith<note n="p" place="margin">Thom. <hi>3.</hi> part. q. <hi>31.</hi> art. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thomas:</hi> that is, According to the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of nature, borne of a woman, and aboue the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of nature, borne of a Virgin: or as<note n="q" place="margin">Euſeb. emiſſ. hom. <hi>1.</hi> de natiu. Chriſti.</note> 
               <hi>Euſebius Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenus, Datus ex diuinitate, natiu ex virgine, natus, &amp; ſic ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre iunior, datus, quo nec pater antiquior, qui erat, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt, qui non erat, natus eſt:</hi> that is, Giuen of God, borne of a Virgin, borne, and ſo younger then his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; giuen, and ſo as ancient as his Father; he that euer was, was giuen, and he that was not, was borne. Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Incarnation, that He, who was the<note n="*" place="margin">Non illius eſt ſilius fabri quem putatis, ſed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricatoris omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp;c. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. ſup. Mat. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> maker of the world, and Father of <hi>Marie,</hi> ſhould be the ſon of <hi>Marie,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:16348:17"/> at God and man ſhould in one perſon meete; and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mother ſhould be a pure Virgin, and that this Sonne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould be the Sauiour of his mother. <hi>Ipſum ſanguinem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em pro matre obtulit, antea de ſanguine matris accepit.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th<note n="r" place="margin">Hom. <hi>1.</hi> de Natiuitate Chriſti.</note> 
               <hi>Emiſſenus:</hi> that is, The ſame blood which he offered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his mother, he before receiued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mother: yea (as <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ombard) Verus homo de homine, propter homine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>minem, ſuper hominem,</hi> that is, True man of mankind,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Lombard. <hi>3.</hi> ſent. diſt. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nkind, according to mankind, and aboue mankind. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onderful Incarnation! that I may ſay of this myſtery, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th S.<note n="t" place="margin">Hieron. Epiſt. ad Eustochium.</note> 
               <hi>Ierome</hi> of another matter; <hi>Si cuncta corporis mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> verterentur in linguas, &amp; omnes artus humana voce re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arent, nihil hercle hac materia dignum proferrem,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, If all the members in our body were turned to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngues, they were not ſufficient to expreſſe this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and myſtery. I will therefore ſay with<note n="u" place="margin">Maximus in Ser. de natali. Mihi impoſſibile eſt generationis ſcire ſecretum, mens deficit, vox ſilet, &amp;c. Ambroſ. Vide Muſc. loc. com. tit. de verb. Incar. in principio.</note> 
               <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mus; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aires, generatio Chriſtinea poteſt enarrari, &amp; vbi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ingua ficit, fides proficit;</hi> that is, Brethren, the generation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riſt cannot be declared, and where the tongue is defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, faith is ſufficient.</p>
            <p>Fond, and fooliſh be the queſtions of the Scholemen this point, arguing, whether the Incarnation of the Lord, be a thing poſſible? what a Perſon, or a <hi>Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> doth adde aboue nature? whether one perſon can be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arnate without another? whether God had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rnate, if man had not ſinned? An idle queſtion, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ued in this queſtioning Age, with many other of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e nature.</p>
            <p>Horat. <hi>Quas pudeat recitare, &amp; nugis addere pondus.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Aug. <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. ad Voluſian. Quomodo non eſt ſupra omnem ſenſum tanta generatio? tu ergo ori manum pone: Scrutari non licet ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na myſteria. Ambr. con. Har.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>Which it ſhames me to recite, or find,</l>
                  <l>In adding weight to empty wind.</l>
               </q> In ſuch myſteries and matters we ſhould follow Saint <hi>Auſtens</hi> modeſty, <hi>Demus Deum aliquid poſſe, quod nos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eamur inuestigare non poſſe,</hi> that is, Let vs grant, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, that God can doe many things, which our ſhallow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>prehenſion cannot comprehend. <hi>Licet ſcire quod na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16348:18"/> ſit Christus, non licet diſcutere quomodo natus ſit,</hi> ſayth <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> that is, It is needful for vs to know, that Chriſt was borne, how, wee muſt not too curiouſly ſearch or examine.</p>
            <p>Sufficient for vs to know, that He was made of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. <hi>Made of a woman:</hi> and this is more expreſly, and particularly ſet downe in our Beliefe, Borne of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary:</hi> which<note n="*" place="margin">Breuis regula fidet, quae men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem taſtrua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, nec onerat memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, Aug. Ser. <hi>115.</hi> de temp.</note> Beliefe is (is<note n="x" place="margin">Amb. Ser. <hi>38.</hi> Maria, exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, amaritudinis Mare, Hieron.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> cals it) <hi>cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis Scripturae:</hi> that is, the key of the Scripture and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed herein by Canonical authority out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Mat. 1.18. Luke 2.7.</p>
            <p>Borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary: Mary,</hi> which ſignifies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, highly exalted, to become the mother of Chriſt: or after the <hi>Syrian</hi> Etimology, ſignifying the Lady of the Sea: the ſole Lady of the Sea of Bliſſe, that the Lord would make her the Lady of his Incarnation, and looke vpon the lowlines of his handmaid,<note place="margin">Luke 1.42.</note> in the fruit of whoſe wombe, all the families of the earth are bleſſed.</p>
            <p>Highly doe the Fathers extoll this <hi>Mary</hi> with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatory Attributes, and Epethites, calling her<note n="y" place="margin">Aug. Ser. <hi>15.</hi> de temp. &amp; ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. Ser. de laud. Mariae. Quicunque Mariae optat praemium, imite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur exemplum, &amp;c. Ambr. de Virgi.</note> 
               <hi>fene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram coeli,</hi> that is, the window of heauen, through which it pleaſed the light of the world to appeare, to illuminate vs that did ſit in the ſhadow of death.</p>
            <p>The moſt Bleſſed woman of all, <hi>Soli Mariae datum eſt eſſe matrem Chriſti, omnibus hominibus denegatum eſt eſſe patrem Chriſts,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hugo,</hi> that is, It was onely granted to the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> to be the mother of Chriſt, when as it was denied to all men, to be the Father of Chriſt. <hi>Eua inobediens meruit poenam, Maria obediendo conſecuta eſt gratiam; illa guſtando prohibitum, maledicta: haec credendo Angelo benedicta,</hi> ſaith<note n="z" place="margin">Aug. con. duat hareſ.</note> 
               <hi>Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that is, <hi>Eue</hi> diſobeying, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued puniſhment; <hi>Mary</hi> obeying, obtained grace: the one by taſting the forbidden fruit, was curſed: this by beleeuing the Angell, was Bleſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Talis fuit Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, vt etas vnius vita ommium fit diciplina, Amb. de virt. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>There is not any ſeaſoned with true religion, that will touch the hemme of the garment of her glory with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16348:18"/> the leaſt reproach: for <hi>all generations ſhall call her Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> Luke 1.46.</p>
            <p>A Propheteſſe on earth, and a Saint in heauen: alwayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch high eſtimation among the faithfull, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hird gene all Councell of Epheſus was aſſembled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainſt Neſtorius, to<note n="a" place="margin">Swarez. praef. diſp. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> in <hi>3.</hi> Thom. Maria ſit ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in honore, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onorata, ſed Dominus ſolus adoret, &amp;c. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan. con. Colly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridianos, haereſ. <hi>79.</hi>
               </note> mainetaine the dignity of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d Virgin <hi>Marie.</hi> Yet, on the other ſide, we muſt not with the Papiſts giue her a too high <hi>Magnificat,</hi> from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onouring he, as a Saint, to Deifie her as a <hi>Mediatrix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſay with<note n="b" place="margin">Aug. lib. de Virginit. Vult dicere, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mea, quam appellatu foelice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, inde foelix eſt, quia verbis Dei cuſtodiuit, non quia in illa ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum caro fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, Aug. ſuper Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam. c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſten, Foelicior partus ſpiritualis, quam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arnalis. Beatior Maria concipiendo Chriſtum fide, quam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arne, &amp;c. i.</hi> Her ſpirituall bearing Chriſt more happy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen her corporall: and <hi>Mary</hi> more bleſſed, conceiuing Chriſt in her heart by faith, then by bearing his body in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er wombe.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts, to aduance the glory of the mother <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> doe diminiſh the glory of the Sonne Chriſt Ieſus: they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ray to her, as to God, they truſt in her, as in a Sauiour; <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro, Maria, iube filiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, monſtra te eſſe matrem ſumat per te <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reces: i. Mary,</hi> wee beſeech thee, command thy Sonne, ſhew thy ſelfe to be a mother, let him receiue our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs from thee: ſo<note n="*" place="margin">Vide Caſſandr. conſult. art. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> runne their Miſſalls. Thus they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, and arrogate too much vnto her, and derogate too much from Chriſt; more then ſhee would haue her ſelfe: for ſhe ſaid, My Soule reioyceth in God my Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, Luke 1.47.</p>
            <p>How fully doe the Papiſts fulfill<note n="c" place="margin">Epithan. con. Collyridian. &amp; Antidicomaria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas: haereſ. <hi>78.</hi> haereſ. <hi>79.</hi> Maria erat vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go honorata, ſed non ad adoratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem nobis data. Mariam nemo adoret, Deo hoc debetur myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium, &amp;c. Vide Epiphan. ſuper dicto loco plenè de hac re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcribentem.</note> 
               <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſaying? <hi>Non dominabitur nobis antiquus error, vt relinquamus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentem, &amp; adoremus ea quae ab ipſo facta ſunt: coluerunt enim, &amp; adoraru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t creaturam, praeter Creatore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſtulti facti ſunt. Si Angelus adorari non vult, quantò minùs Maria, qua genita eſt ab Anna ex Ioachimo? &amp;c. i.</hi> Let not that old errour beare ſway among vs, that wee ſhould leaue the liuing God, to worſhip the workes of his hands: ſo the people aforetime worſhipped, and adored the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, beſide the Creator, and made themſelues fooles. If
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16348:19"/> an Angell will not be worſhipped, much leſſe the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which was begotten by <hi>Ioachim,</hi> of <hi>Anna, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But among all the reſt, and neſt of Papiſts, <hi>Clarus Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narſcius,</hi> otherwiſe <hi>Carolus Scribanius,</hi> hath exceeded all his fellow Ieſuites in impiety, or blaſphemy; who in his third Booke,<note place="margin">See M. <hi>Craſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awes</hi> confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the Book, called The Ieſuites Goſpell.</note> and eight Chapter, of <hi>Amphithea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum honoris, &amp;c.</hi> compares the milke of <hi>Mary</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lac matris miſcere volo cum ſanguine Chriſti:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Page 356.</note>
                  <hi>Non poſſum antidoto nobiliore frui:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of milke and blood, a mixture I will make:</l>
               <l>The ſoueraignſt cordiall ſinfull ſoule can take.</l>
            </q>
            <p>A Booke worthy of fire, and forgetfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>Nay the learned doe daily read among the Ieſuites<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Friers workes, what <hi>Hyperbolies,</hi> or rather impieties in this point they doe mainetaine. A man may appeale from God, to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> ſaith<note n="d" place="margin">Bernardin. de Buſt. in Mariali part. <hi>3.</hi> Ser. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bernardinus de Buſtis,</hi> God hath made the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> partaker of his Diuine power, and maieſty, ſaith <hi>Horatius</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Hor. Turſ. in hiſtor. Virg. Lauretana in praefat. Vide Catalogum teſtium verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, editionis <hi>1608.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Turſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They who haue read the Papiſts <hi>Mariale,</hi> may there find, what groſſe and falſe Diuinity herein they hold, for example: Let the ſinner fly to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and he ſhall be ſaued: and againe, That the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> was with the Lord in the worke of Redemption, and bare all the wounds in her heart, which Chriſt did beare in his body.</p>
            <p>And to ſpeak no more herein, they that haue read the Papiſts<note n="*" place="margin">Extat Pſalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium ad verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, apud Chemniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, in examine Concilij Trident. in part. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>149.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ladyes-Pſalter,</hi> may finde, how in many of the Pſalmes, they haue turned <hi>Dominus</hi> to <hi>Domina,</hi> our Lord, to our Lady: and this Booke ſtands not onely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controlled, but euen defended, and commended by the<note n="*" place="margin">Gregor. de Val. in Vol. de rebus fidei con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſis. Sect. <hi>5.</hi> lib. de Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> Ieſuites, and thoſe of the principall: I will end this with the Poets verſe,
<q>Quid ſatis eſt, ſi Roma parum?—</q>
            </p>
            <p>What is enough, if <hi>Rome</hi> be too little? ſo this little is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16348:19"/> enough, to giue you a taſte of Romiſh impiety, to ſhew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou, how they robbe our Sauiour of his glory, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce of ſole Mediatorſhip, and would diuide it to a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure: but, <hi>riualem poſſum non ego ferre:</hi>—</p>
            <p>God is ielous of his glory, and can brooke no riuall. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et me a little longer treſpaſſe in this digreſſion: Borne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> a perpetuall Virgin, that is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erall opinion of<note n="f" place="margin">Perk. refor. Catho. tit tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Beza confeſſ. c. <hi>3.</hi> art. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> Diuines.<note n="*" place="margin">D. Boſe.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And herein I will borrow a line or two of our learned Doctor, as I take, he borrowed it before of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.<note n="g" place="margin">Virgo conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, virgo graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, virgo in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, virgo poſt partum, praecla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra illa Virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, &amp; glorioſa foecunditas: Aug. Ser. <hi>6.</hi> in Nat. Dom. Sancta, &amp; beata Maria &amp; Virgo ante partum, &amp; Virgo poſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ego hoc mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, quomodo de Virgine natus ſit, &amp; poſt Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Virginis Mater virgo ſit, &amp;c. Chryſo. hom. de Ioanne Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tista. Inuenta eſt vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, illa pragnans, ad quam vir non acceſſerat: vte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus quidem foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu tumuerat, &amp; virginalis inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritas manſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, &amp;c. Chryſoſt. hom. de S. Suſanna.</note> 
               <hi>Auſten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Virgin
<list>
                  <item>Before</item>
                  <item>In</item>
                  <item>After</item>
               </list> Chriſts birth:</p>
            <p>A Virgin before his Birth, againſt three ſorts of men;
<list>
                  <item>1. Iewes,</item>
                  <item>2. Gentiles.</item>
                  <item>3. Corinthians.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Confirmed againſt them by the Scripture, Mat. 1.20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uk. 1.27.</p>
            <p>A Virgin in his birth, againſt
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iouinian,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Durandus,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſe errours herein are recited by <hi>Iraeneus,</hi> and Saint <hi>Auſten,</hi> and by them both refuted, <hi>Iraen. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>Aug. de haereſ. cap.</hi> 82. <hi>&amp; con. Iulian. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Confirmed againſt them by the ſeuenth of <hi>Eſay:</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4. <hi>A Virgin ſhall conceiue and beare a Sonne:</hi> the which words (as one before me well interpreted) are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued <hi>in ſenſu compoſito, non diuiſo,</hi> that is, in a compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſenſe, &amp; not diuided: that is to ſay, that ſhe was a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, <hi>concipieus, &amp; pariens:</hi> conceyuing, and bringing forth.</p>
            <p>A Virgin after his birth, againſt
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heluidians,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Antidicomarianits,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> whoſe errors are recorded by Saint <hi>Ierome,</hi> and by him confuted, <hi>lib. aduerſ. Heluidium: &amp; Aug. haereſ.</hi> 84.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Mary</hi> was a Virgin, before, and in Chriſts birth,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16348:20"/> none but Athieſts did euer deny it: as alſo the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity of <hi>Maries</hi> Virginity, is generally receiued of the Proteſtant part, and the Papiſts haue made it an Article of the Churches Faith, the perpetuity of <hi>Maries</hi> Virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the which point I may fitly conclude with the word: of<note n="h" place="margin">Piſcat. analiſ. in Mat. <hi>1.</hi> verſu vltimo.</note> 
               <hi>Piſcator, Curioſum magis eſt quàm pium, inquirere, cùm de eare Scripturae nihil traedit:</hi> that is, It is a point more curious, then godly to inquire after it, ſince the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks nothing of it: and where the Scripture ſtaies her penne, there let man ſtay his tongue.</p>
            <p>Thus you haue heard, that our Sauiour was made of a woman, borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> and tooke our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure vpon him, howſoeuer <hi>Valentinus,</hi> and his followers deny it: ſo that I will end this point with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius</hi> ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng in his Creede, <hi>Chriſt is God of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his Father, begotten before all worlds, and man of the ſubſtance of his Mother, borne in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in a word, let vs declare (as I promiſed) the manner of Chriſts Natiuity, how he was borne of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? and that is plainely, and briefely ſet forth by<note n="i" place="margin">Luke 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Luke:</hi> And ſhee brought her firſt-borne Sonne; and wrapped him in ſwaddling clothes, and layed him in a cratch, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was no roome for him in the Inne. And this manner of Chriſts Natiuity, doth amplifie the meaſure of Chriſts humility; Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> He, who was the Lord of all, <hi>The earth is the Lords, and all that is therein,</hi> ſayth<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 42.1.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid; Quae ſuperbia ſanari poteſt, ſi humilitate Filij Dei non ſana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur?</hi> ſaith<note n="l" place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>58.</hi> Qui ſine humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate virtutes congregat, quaſi in ventum pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerem portat, Gregor. hom. <hi>6.</hi> Tantò pretioſior Deo, quantò propter Deum humilior ſibi: Gregor. lib. <hi>18.</hi> moral.</note> 
               <hi>Auſten:</hi> that is, What pride can be healed, which is not helped by the humility of the Sonne of God? <hi>Learne of me: for I am humble, and meeke,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour; yea he ſhewed himſelfe ſo humble, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, that hee did vouch ſafe to be wrapped vp in ſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling clothes, to be layed in <hi>praeſepi;</hi> in a cratch, or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; in ſuch humility, penury, and pouerty, that I may ſay of him, as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil</hi> ſpeaks of the Sonne of <hi>Pollio;</hi>
               <q>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:16348:20"/>
                  <l>Nec Deus hunc menſa, dea nec dignata cubili eſt:</l>
                  <bibl>Virg. eclog eui Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o: verſu vltimo.</bibl>
                  <l>Pollio <hi>had nei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>her boord nor bed,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To eat his meate, or lay his head.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Strange humility,<note place="margin">Ber. Ser. <hi>1.</hi> in Natal. Dom.</note> that hee who thundred in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>louds, ſhould cry in the cradle, ſwaddled in ragges, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yd in a manger: <hi>Vbi aula Regia? vbi Thronus? vbi curiae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egalis frequentia? numquid aula eſt ſtabulum? Thronus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raeſepium? &amp; totius curiae frequentia Ioſep &amp; Maria?</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s writes<note n="m" place="margin">Ber. in Ser. de Epiph.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard,</hi> that is, Where is the Kingly Court? where is the Throne? where is the regall frequency? what, is the ſtable the Court? the manger, the Throne? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> the ſole attendants? Is the King of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſrael thus welcomed into the world? Strange humility!</p>
            <p>Strange, that there ſhould be no roome for him in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nne, which is a receptacle for all ſorts, and as Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Ambroſ. lib. de offic. Chriſtus omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus omnia factus eſt, pauper pauperi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Ama<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ſuper. la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Eſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus qui omnes p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>t, ſimut, per quem creatur omnis potus, &amp; qui ſpiritualiter panis est eſuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entium, fonſque ſitientium, in terra fatigatus, qui ſeipſum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis viam fecit in coelum, Aug. de Catechizand. rud.</note> 
               <hi>Eſt publica humanitatis ſpecies, vt peregrinus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſpitio non egeat, ſuſcipitur officioſe, &amp; patet aduententi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anna, &amp;c.</hi> that is, It is common courteſie, that a ſtranger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould not lacke lodging in an Inne, but to be receiued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fficiouſly with an open gate. Our Sauiour depriued of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his comm n humanity, argues his greater humility.</p>
            <p>We ſee how the infants of mortall Kings, yea of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner perſons, find better entertainement in their ingreſſe to the world: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir infancy welcomed with ſoft and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ornaments, entertained with reſpectiue, and ſedulous attendants, bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne not in Innes, but in houſes ſeeled with Vermillion, layed vpon beddes of Downe, adorned pon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſly with purple, and pureſt whi e, cheriſhed euen with <hi>Ambroſean</hi> ſuccour, all variety, and delicacy to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent their morning mourning infancy: And y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t behold, our Sauiour layed in a cratch, wrapt vp with poore clothes, and clouts: <hi>Num quid mater eius diademate coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata? aut in lecto eburneo recumbens? num puer byſſo, &amp; purpura inuolutus? vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non, ſed angustum, &amp; humile tugurium, vile, ſquallidum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> praeſepium, magis animalibus, quàm hominibus aptum: puer vilibus pannis inuolutus, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16348:21"/> vix tunicam habens vnam, non ad ornatum corporis, ſed ad tegumentum nuditatis,</hi> as writes Saint<note n="o" place="margin">Chryſoſt. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Mat. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> that is, What? is the mother crowned with a diademe? o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lying in an Iuory bedde? or the child inueſted with ſilk, and purple? no ſurely, but a ſtraite, and poore cottage, a vile and homely manger, fitter for beaſt, then man: the child wrapped vp in ragges; the mother ſcarce hauing one coat, not for ornament of body, but to couer naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Strange penury! Why would the immortall Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor abaſe himſelfe in pouerty, lower then many mortall creatures? Saint<note n="p" place="margin">Aug. Ser. <hi>3.</hi> de Stephano.</note> 
               <hi>Auſten</hi> giues vs the reaſon, <hi>Paup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>natus eſt in terris, vt nos diuites naſceremur in coelis,</hi> that is, He was borne poore on earth, that we might bee borne rich in heauen.</p>
            <p>Thoſe diuine and delicate bones, which ſhould haue beene emboſomed in the nurſery of heauen, lye in a manger. Who can heare this, and be proud of his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ornaments; and ſee his Sauiour ſwadled in ſuch meane habilliments? Who can with<note n="q" place="margin">Dan. 4.27.</note> 
               <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> glory in his pompe, and ſtrout himſelfe in his Palace of <hi>Babel,</hi> and halfe-deifie himſelfe with a vaine conceit of his Towers,<note place="margin">Superbia de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelo diabolum fecit, &amp; homini mortem intulit, omnium malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum mater, ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerum fons, vena nequitiae, &amp;c. Caſſio. ſuper. Pſ. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> and Turrets, of his ſpangled gay ornaments, of his obſequious attendants, of his court-like traine, and ſumptuouſneſſe; and ſee his Sauiour borne in a ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſwaddled in poore fragments, layde in a manger? This humility ſhould deplume the feathers of mans Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock-like pride; pull downe his high, and aſpiring ſpirit; teach him to ſee himſelfe, to know himſelfe, to humble himſelfe, to contemne the vanities of this vaine vvorld, and looke vpon the picture of his Sauiours humility, to learne of him; for he was humble and meeke.</p>
            <p>Would this nice, and ouer-dainty Age lay this leſſon to their hearts, it might recouer them from their falling ſickeneſſe: for<note n="*" place="margin">Adraſtia Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſis. Superbia co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Nobilitatis malum, Saluſt. in bello Iug.</note> Pride muſt haue a fall, Prou. 16.18. then they would not be ſo enamored of themſelues, of their ornaments: the Oſtridge ſhould not be robbed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16348:21"/> of her taile, to fanne the Ladies face. <hi>Heu, hominum vnde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e faſtus, iſta ſuperbia? cui vita aut abeſt, aut ſpondet ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntiam: mors aut inſtat, aut minatur instantiam,</hi> ſaith one: that is, Alas, whence is this puffe,<note n="r" place="margin">Alanus lib. de complanctu na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae.</note> and pride of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an? to whom life is abſent, or promiſeth abſence: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eath is euer inſtant, or threatens his approach: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey haue learned the careleſſe Epicures <hi>Enthymente:</hi> Let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> eate and drink: inferring the concluſion out of<note n="ſ" place="margin">Eſay 22.12.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay,</hi> We muſt dye to morrow. Thus they ſpend away their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayes in pride and pleaſure, reuell, and riot away their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ules in ſinnes, and thinkes not of the end of all. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me will come, when they will cry out the wordes of <hi>Bernard, Quid profuit ſuperbia?</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Ber. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de conſid. Subitò, quid non ſuſpicatur infortunium, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidit, calamitas irruit, mors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercipit, quam nullus euadit, Innoc. de vilit. condit. hum.</note> 
               <hi>quid diuitiarum iactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a? mundi potentia? vana voluptas? hen, de tanta laetitia, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uanta triſtitia!</hi> that is, What hath pride profited vs? what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he bragges of wealth? worldly power? vaine pleaſure? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>las, from how great mirth, to greater miſery!</p>
            <p>Oh learne in time, while time laſts, to humble your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lues, to follow the example of true humility, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orce your mindes from earthly vanity, and as<note n="u" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Peter,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umble your ſelues vnder the mighty hand of God, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e may exalt you in due time: Looke on our<note n="*" place="margin">Exempla bonae vita à Chriſto, &amp; ab eius acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus aſſumere debemus, Ber. in Cant. Ser. <hi>23.</hi> Quis talia fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do explicet? — <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg.</note> Sauiours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umility, penury, and pouerty, the patterneleſſe patterne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ humility, that hee would vouchſafe to be borne of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oman, and in ſuch humble manner, wrapped vp in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>waddling clouts, and layed in a manger.</p>
            <p>But I ſtay too long, though I deliuer but a drop of matter, in compariſon of the abundant plenty which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owes from this Sea of matter: but that which I omit, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe commit to your meditations, and contemplations.</p>
            <p>The next point I come to touch, is the ſecond part of his <hi>Quomodo. Made vnder the Law:</hi> wherein I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uite my former prolixity with proportionable breuity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made vnder the Law.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Omnis huius na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiuitatis Schola, eſt humilitatis officina, Aug. Ser. <hi>22.</hi> de temp.</note> And this ſtill enlargeth Chriſts humility; That he, who was the Maker of the Law, yea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Law it ſelfe, would be ſubiect to the Law, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16348:22"/> the Law: and therfore according to the Law, he was circumciſed the eight day, Luke 2.21. and by this cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion made himſelfe <hi>debitorem totius Legis,</hi> a debtor of the Law, and bound to keepe the whole Law, as<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, Euery one that is circumciſed, is bound to keepe the whole Law. That I may ſay with<note n="y" place="margin">Aug. lib. de ſpirit &amp; litera.</note> 
               <hi>Auſten, Lex data eſt, vt gratia quaereretur, gratia data eſt, vt lex implere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> that is, The Law was giuen, that grace might be ſought for; grace was giuen, that the Law might be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. Chriſt fulfilled the Law, not by grace, but by his merites, and perfect obedience of the Law: we fulfill the Law, not by<note n="*" place="margin">Vis excidere gratia? tunc tacta tua meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, Aug. in Pſ. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> merits, but by imputation of Chriſts merits by grace extended to vs.</p>
            <p>By the Law, we were all the ſonnes of death, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of damnation, Bond-men, and captiues to the Prince of darkneſſe: <hi>Ligat Diabolus peccata connectens: ſoluit Chriſtus delicta dimittens,</hi> ſayth<note n="x" place="margin">Caſſio ſuper Pſal. <hi>146.</hi>
               </note> one: that is, The diuell bound vs with the cart-ropes of iniquities, tying them together:<note n="*" place="margin">O bone Ieſu, mori nos debui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; tu ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis? nos peccaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; tu luis. Opus ſine exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo, gratia ſine merito, charitas ſine modo, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard.</note> Chriſt did vnlooſe vs, cancelling our ſinnes, ſatisfying his Fathers Iuſtice by obedience in his life, by his paſſion in his death: and as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 8.3. That which was impoſſible to the Law, God ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his owne Sonne in the ſimilitude of ſinfull fleſh, and for ſinne, condemned ſinne in the fleſh, that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the Law might be fulfilled in vs.</p>
            <p>Chriſt, by his perfect<note n="*" place="margin">Sola obedientia ibi tenet palma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vbi ſola in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientia inuenit poenam, Ambro.</note> obedience to the Law, tooke away our culpable guiltineſſe of the breach of the Law, and by his ſatisfactory paſſion, ſacrificing himſelfe (like the mother Pellican willing to die, to giue life by her blood to her brood.) So Chriſt, offering himſelfe a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice once for all, as the<note n="z" place="margin">Heb. 7.27.</note> Author to the Hebrewes, &amp;<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 9.12.</note> by his blood obtained eternall Redemption for vs, hath freed vs both <hi>à culpa, &amp; poena,</hi> from the guilt and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinne, freeing vs from the curſe of the Law, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made a curſe for vs, Gal. 3.13. <hi>Sic tegit pecoata, vt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit aduertere, noluit animaduertere, noluit punire, noluit
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16348:22"/> agnoſcere, maluit agnoſcere,</hi> ſaith<note n="b" place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſten,</hi> that is, God ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouered our ſinnes, that he would not looke on them, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rke them, or puniſh them, or acknowledge them,<note n="*" place="margin">Vt ſic velentur peccata, ne in iudicio reuelen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Heronym. in Pſal. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther pardon them. Yea, he that knew no ſinne, ſurffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d for our ſinnes, did beare our ſinnes, ſorrowes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>firmities, and by his ſtripes we are healed, Eſay 53.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In me, &amp; pro me doluit, qui pro ſe nihil habuit, quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leret,</hi> ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">Ambroſ. de fide ad Gratian. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe;</hi> that is, In mee, and for mee our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uiour ſorrowed, who for himſelfe had nothing to be ſorrowfull. Thus he carried our ſorrowes, yea our ſinnes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho did not ſinne, neyther was there guile found in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>outh, as<note n="d" place="margin">2. Pet. 2.22.</note> 
               <hi>Peter:</hi> that I may ſay with<note n="e" place="margin">Aug. lib. de Virginitat.</note> 
               <hi>Auſten, Inſpice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lnera pendentis, ſanguinem mortentis, praecium redimentis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atrices reſurgentis: haec quanta ſint, cogitate, haec in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra cordis veſtri appendite, vt totus vobis figatur in corde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i totus pro nobis fixus fuit in cruce,</hi> that is, Behold Chriſts wounds hanging, his blood dying,<note n="*" place="margin">Filius Dei ad crucem ducitur, expalmatur, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis coronatur, ligatur, ligno ſuſpenditur, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplina caeditur, ſalus vulnera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, vita mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: occidit ad tempus vitam mors, vt in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuum à vita occideretur mors, Aug. lib. de octo. virt. Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis.</note> his price re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eming, his ſcarres, and bloody markes ariſing: Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, how great theſe things be, weigh them in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce of your hearts, that Chriſt may be fixed in your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earts, who was for you faſtened on the croſſe.</p>
            <p>Thus Chriſt for vs, was borne, <hi>Made of a woman, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ade vnder the Law,</hi> ſubiect to the Law, who was the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aker, and ſubiect of the Law, fulfilling the Law per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctly, and plenarily: and why all this?</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Quorſum haec tam long a dolorum</l>
               <l>intendit ſeries? —</l>
            </q>
            <p>To what purpoſe tended all theſe labours, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owes? this incomparable, and incomprehenſible humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity? this actiue and paſſiue obedience? the ſequell of my text expreſſeth the true <hi>Quare,</hi> why? <hi>To redeeme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem which were vnder the Law, that we might receiue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>doption of Sonnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The generall, and ſummary cauſe of Chriſts Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, Humiliation, legall ſubiection, paſſion, and all; was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o redeeme vs from ſinne, Sathan, and condemnation:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16348:23"/> the<note n="*" place="margin">Ille Iuſtus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit ad nos pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores, vt ex pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catoribus faceret <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſtos, venit ad impios, vt face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret pios, venit ad ſuperbos, vt face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret humiles, Ambroſ. ſuper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cam.</note> comming of God to man, was, that man ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to God, put off the old man, and put on the new, that as all died in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> they might liue in the ſecond <hi>Adam: Chriſtus venit, vt imaginem ſuam diaboli arte fucatam, in homine, &amp; per lignum praeuaricationis mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te damnatam, per paſſionem crucis, &amp; mortem, ad priſtin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> reuocaret pulchritudinem,</hi> ſayth<note n="f" place="margin">Origen. hom. <hi>1.</hi> in Gen. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Origen,</hi> that is, Chriſt came, that he might re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tore his owne Image ſoyled by the ſubtilty of the diuell, and by his preuarication in eating the forbidden fruit, condemned to death, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer it by the former beautie, by his death and paſſion on the Croſſe: yea (as<note n="g" place="margin">Aug ſuper Joan. &amp; in gloſſ. <hi>1.</hi> Tim. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſten) Nulla alia cauſa aduentus Domini, niſi peccatores ſalues facere,</hi> that is, There was no other cauſe of Chriſts comming, but to finiſh the worke of mans ſaluation. I will vſe the words of reuerend<note n="i" place="margin">Bed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuper Cant. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Venit vnus ſine peccato, qui ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uos omnes face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret ſine peccato, Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, Venit vt errantes corrigat, infirmantes adiuuet, dubitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in fide confirmet, &amp; certantes ab hoſtium inſidijs defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat, &amp; victores hoſtium perpetuae ſuae viſionis corona mune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> that is, Chriſt came to correct the erring, to help the weake, to confirme the wauering, to defend the ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, from the crafts of the enemy, and to reward the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercommers of their deadly enemy, with the crowne of the perpetuall ſight of God.</p>
            <p>I may ſay of Chriſts firſt comming, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> writ to the Senate of Rome of himſelfe: <hi>Veni, vidi, vici,</hi> that is, I came, I ſaw, I ouercame. So Chriſt came in humility: he ſaw our miſerie, and for vs he gate the victory.</p>
            <p>In his firſt comming, hee preſented himſelfe to the world in penury, pouerty, humility, <hi>Borne of a woman, made vnder the Law,</hi> ſubiect to the Law, condemned by a Law againſt all Law: We haue a Law, and by our Law he ought to die, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie the<note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 19.7.</note> Iewes to <hi>Pilate.</hi> But at his ſecond comming he ſhall appeare in maieſty and great glorie, not to be condemned, but to condemne: <hi>Venit Chriſtus occultè iudicandus, veniet manifeſtè iudicaturus,</hi> ſaith<note n="i" place="margin">Aug. de ciuit. Dei. Quoties Diem illum conſidero, toto corpore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremiſco, ſiue comedo, ſiue bibo, ſemper vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur illa tuba ſonare in auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, Surgite mortui, venite ad iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cium, Hieron.</note> 
               <hi>Auſten,</hi> that is, Chriſt at his firſt comming was
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16348:23"/> priuily condemned, but at his ſecond comming he ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>penly iudge, and condemne; and woe be vnto them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en, whom he hath not redeemed from the curſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aw, they ſhall neuer receiue the adoption of Sonnes.</p>
            <p>At the day of the ſecond comming of Chriſt, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhall come to iudge, hee will not be perſwaded by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tty, nor moued by intreaty, nor corrupted by mony: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erefore (as<note n="k" place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Symbolo.</note> 
               <hi>Auſten</hi> writes, <hi>Hic dum tempus habet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at anima pro ſe, quia hic locus eſt miſericordiae, ibi erit lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s iuſtitiae,</hi> that is, While time ſerues, let the ſoule looke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her ſelfe, for this is the place of mercy, then is the time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>Chriſt at his firſt comming came <hi>ferendo,</hi> bearing our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rrowes; at his ſecond comming he will come <hi>feriendo,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eating and<note n="*" place="margin">Pſa. 2.9.</note> breaking the wicked in peeces like a Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs veſſell.</p>
            <p>It is a piercing conſideration of<note n="l" place="margin">Anſel. de ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudinib. mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di.</note> 
               <hi>Anſelmus</hi> ſpeaking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f this day of Chriſts ſecond comming, <hi>A dextris erunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eccata, à ſiniſtris daemonia, ſubtus infernus, de ſuper Iudex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atus, foris mundus ardens, intus conſcientia furens; heu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſer peccator, ſic deprehenſus, quo fugies? latere erit im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſibile, apparere intolerabile,</hi> that is, On the right hand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and thy ſinnes, on the left the diuels, beneath, hell, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oue, the angrie Iudge, abroad, the world burning, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, thy conſcience raging: alas, wofull ſinner, ſo taken, whither ſhalt thou flie? to hide thee, it is vnpoſſible, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppeare, it is intolerable.</p>
            <p>Therefore if wee deſire to haue him a gentle, louing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd a mercifull Iudge vnto vs at his ſecond comming, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et vs be well grounded in his firſt comming, belieuing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tedfaſtly his Incarnation, admiring his humiliation, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ying his obedience, righteouſneſſe, merits, paſſion, with all the benefits, and fruits thereto belonging vnto our ſoules by a faithful application, put on al Chriſts me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>its, knowing that wee of our ſelues be vnprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ants, and haue no merits, ſaying with<note n="m" place="margin">Ber. Ser. <hi>53</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bernard, Sufficit
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16348:24"/> ad meritum ſcire, quòd non ſufficiant merita,</hi> that is, To know the ſufficiency of man, merites, is to know that they will not ſuffice: For what haue wee that wee haue not<note n="*" place="margin">Omne bonum noſtrum vel ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, vel ab ipſo, Aug. lib. <hi>1</hi> de doct. Chriſt. c. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> receiued? <hi>Deus autor eſt meriti, qui &amp; voluntatem applicat operi, &amp; opus applicat voluntati,</hi> ſaith<note n="n" place="margin">Aug. lib. de lib. arb. Boni ſi quid habeo, à Deo ſumpſi, non à me praeſumpſi, Aug. Ep. <hi>52.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſten,</hi> that is, God is the author of merit, who applieth the will to the worke, and the worke to the will. Let vs beleeue, that Chriſts inherent righteouſneſſe ſufficeth to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our inherent wickedneſſe: That Chriſts obedience is made our obedience by imputation, his merits our merits; that he by his painefull paſſion, hath for all our ſinnes made a perfect ſatisfaction; that all his ſorrowes and ſufferings were to worke our Redemption; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme vs, that were vnder the Law, and from the curſe of the Law, that by grace we might receiue the adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sonnes.</p>
            <p>So that by this you may vnderſtand, that wee receiue the adoption of Sonnes, not for our good<note n="*" place="margin">Qui credit in Chriſtum, ſaluus ſit ſine opere, ſola ſide gratis accipiens remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Ambroſ. com. in <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>1.4.</hi> &amp; Anſelm. enarrat: in eum loc.</note> works, or by the workes of the Law; but onely by grace, and a liuely faith in Chriſt Ieſus: for to this end, he was <hi>made of a woman, and made vnder the Law, to redeeme vs that were vnder the Law, that we might receiue the adoption of Sonnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 4.25.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of Chriſt, Who was deliuered to death for our ſinnes, and roſe againe for our iuſtification: and as the ſame<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 3.24.</note> Apoſtle ſaith, And a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e iuſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption which is in Chriſt Ieſus: and yet ſomewhat more fully the ſaid<note n="q" place="margin">Gal. 2.16.</note> Apoſtle, Know that a man is not iuſtified by the workes of the Law, but by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c. Becauſe that by the workes of the Law, no fleſh is iuſtified: the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> aboundeth with pregnant proofes to manifeſt this concluſion, That onely faith doth iuſtifie.</p>
            <p>To cite a place, or two, in ſteade of many: as namely to the<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Epheſians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.8.9.</note> By grace ye are ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ued through faith, and that not of your ſelues: for it is the gift of God, not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16348:24"/> of works, leſt any man ſhould boaſt himſelfe: What place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be more perſpicuous againſt Iuſticiaries, and merit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngers, then that place? and againe to the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 3.28.</note> Romanes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> maketh his vndenyable concluſion, ſaying: Therfore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conclude, that a man is iuſtified by faith, without the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orks of the Law: and ſo in many other<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 1.17. Rom. 3.16. Rom. 5.1. Gal. 3.8.11.</note> places.</p>
            <p>And howſoeuer the abortiue ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ldren of the falſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, which would diuide Iuſtification, partly to faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d partly to workes, looke aſquint vpon this doctrine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lding that faith alone doth not iuſtifie: and as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hemiſts more boldly,<note n="t" place="margin">Rhemiſts in <hi>1.</hi> Pet. <hi>4.7.</hi> &amp;c.</note> that charitable workes of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, cauſe remiſſion of ſinnes in the ſight of God: and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eanes of Iuſtification.</p>
            <p>Wherein I ſay, as one before me obſerues, that albeit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r faith is not <hi>ſolitaria,</hi> going alone, for it is alwayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> companied with good<note n="*" place="margin">Opera fidei pediſſequa, Chri. de fide, &amp; lege. Perk. ſimilitud. refor. cathol. tit. Iuſtificat. Tutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſumus, ſi Deo totum damus, Aug.</note> workes, the fruits of faith: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in our Iuſtification, it is <hi>ſola,</hi> alone: euen as the eye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich in regard of being, is neuer alone from the head, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in reſpect of ſeeing it is alone, for the eye onely ſees: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o faith ſubſiſts not without ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er graces, yet in regard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the act of Iuſtification, it is alone without them all.</p>
            <p>The<note n="u" place="margin">Bellar. de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificat. lib <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> §. ac pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio, &amp;c.</note> Papiſts themſelues confeſſe, that <hi>Luther, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nction, Chemnitius, Caluin,</hi> and other learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtants teach, that good workes be neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on in ſome ſort, and that it is no<note n="*" place="margin">Inſeparab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lis eſt bona vita à fide, &amp;c. Aug. de fide, &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib. c. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> true faith, that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oid of them, though the inward worke of Iuſtification <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> aſcribed in holy Scripture to faith onely: and herein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hold no more, then Saint <hi>Paul</hi> taught vs, and the beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>athers approued, and ſome of the Papiſts allowed. I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill produce but a teſtimony or two, in ſteade of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>loud of witneſſes we a e compaſſed about.<note n="*" place="margin">Origen. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p ſt. ad Rom. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Origen</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>peaking of this point of Iuſtification, ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, <hi>Per fidem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stificatus eſt latro ſine operibus Legis,</hi> that is, By faith the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heefe was iuſtified without the works of the Law: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> little after, <hi>Igitur iuſtificatur homo per fidem, cui ad iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>titiam nihil conferunt opera Legis,</hi> that is, Therfore a man
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16348:25"/> is iuſtified by faith, to whom the workes of the Law helpe nothing to his iuſtifying.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Ambroſ. de vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ne Genti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeakes likewiſe for vs, ſaying, <hi>Hoc conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tutum à Deo, vt qui credit in Chriſtum, ſaluus ſit, ſine ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſola fide,</hi> that is, This is ſo ordained of God, that hee which beleeues in Chriſt, ſhall be ſaued without works, only by faith.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Athanaſ. ad Galatas c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſpeaks plainely, <hi>In lege nemo iustificatur, quia iuſtus ex fide viuit, &amp;c.</hi> concluding, <hi>Fidem ſola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi inſe habere virtutem,</hi> that is, By the Law none is iuſtified, for the iuſt man liues by faith: onely faith hath the vertue, or power of iuſtifying.</p>
            <p>Saint<note n="z" place="margin">Aug. ad Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Preſbiterii con. Pelagianos, Epiſt. <hi>105.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſten</hi> hath many places to confirme this point, one for all: <hi>Colligimus hominem non iuſtificari prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptis bonae vitae, ſed per fidem Ieſu Chriſti, non lege ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ſed lege fidei, non litera, ſed ſpiritu, non factorum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritis, ſed gratuita gratia,</hi> that is, We collect that a man is iuſtified, not by the precepts of good life; but by faith in Ieſus Chriſt: not by the Law of works, but by the Law of faith: not by the letter, but by the ſpirit; not by the merits of our works, but by free grace. If I ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine this point copiouſly, I ſhould (as it were) write <hi>Iliades</hi> after <hi>Homer.</hi> Our Diuines haue ſo chaſed, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Papiſts in this paſſage, that though they can ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vp their feet nimbly, and cunningly; yet they haue beene ſo hard followed, that they haue made them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertake, and enter-fire in their pace.</p>
            <p>The old Papiſts wil condemne their yonger brethren the new Ieſuites: for they liked this Truth, which wee hold, we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l enough: for<note n="a" place="margin">Aquinas lect. <hi>4.</hi> in <hi>3</hi> Rom. &amp; l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. <hi>4.</hi> in <hi>3</hi> Gal.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> hath left it written, that works be not the cauſe, why a man is iuſt before God, but rather a manifeſtation of his iuſtice: for no man is iuſtified by works, but by the habite of infuſed faith. So<note n="b" place="margin">Antididagm. Colontenſ. tit. de Iuſtiſ. hom p. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gropper</hi> with the Diuines of Colen ſay, By faith we are iuſtified, as by the apprehenſiue cauſe: and<note n="c" place="margin">Art. <hi>1.</hi> contra Lutherum.</note> 
               <hi>Roffenſis,</hi> as moderator of the queſtion, ſaith, <hi>Fides abſque partu ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16348:25"/> hoc eſt, cum nondum peperit opera, iuſtificare poteſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at is, Faith without the birth of works, that is, before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath brought forth any works, can iuſtifie: yea, many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Papiſts approued it for ſound Diuinity, till the late <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll Councell of Trent reiected it. So that the rayling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hemiſts were too intemperat in their gloſing Gloſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the third of the Romanes, the 22. verſe, calling it a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew no-Iuſtice; a phantaſticall apprehenſion, ſhewing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eir phantaſticall examination of the verſe, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enſion of the Truth: or as an<note n="d" place="margin">Wright Art. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> other of their diſciples <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lles it, a <hi>Soliſidian</hi> portion: or as an<note n="e" place="margin">Apolog. Ep. ſect. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> other, a deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of order, a doctrine againſt the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>Surely, for the reuerence of Romes elder Sonnes, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould forbeare to caſt ſuch ſtones, leſt vnawares they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe hit their ſtep-mother.</p>
            <p>As in many things, ſo in this they offer vs wrong, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ining that wee exclude good workes from iuſtifying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith; we know that there can be<note n="*" place="margin">See D. <hi>Abbot</hi> againſt Biſhop. pag. 482.</note> no reall ſeparation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith from good workes: ſeparation mentall in vnder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anding, is negatiue, or priuatiue: negatiue, when in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e vnderſtanding there is an affirming of one, and deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g of another: priuatiue, when of things that cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſeparated really, yet a man vnderſtands the one, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mitteth to vnderſtand the other: So in our Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, wee doe not negatiuely ſeparate other graces from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith, as if faith exiſted alone without them, but priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uely making them effects, and conſequents, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utring cauſes of our Iuſtification. Wee truely confeſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat a iuſtifying faith is operatiue, as<note n="f" place="margin">Staplet. de Iuſtificat. lib. <hi>9.</hi> cap <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Stapleton</hi> himſelf af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mes we doe: and as<note n="g" place="margin">Super Euang. in feſto Ioan. Euangelist.</note> 
               <hi>Luther</hi> vſed heerein a fit ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ude: Faith is like Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in Chriſts boſome, poſſeſſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the merits of Chriſt: and good workes are like Saint <hi>Peter</hi> following his Maſter. Faith is the<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.</hi> of good works. <hi>part.</hi> 1.</note> neſt of good workes; and if our birds be neuer ſo faire, they will be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt, exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pt they bee brough forth in true Beliefe: our good wo kes, vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe they bee layed vpon the Altar
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16348:26"/> of faith, are not acceptable to God.</p>
            <p>Infidels or heretikes (ſaith<note n="k" place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>8</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſten</hi>) in doing glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous acts, haue not where to lay their young: for wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting faith, they build vpon the land. Whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne, as the<note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 14.23.</note> Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Domus Dei credendo fundatur, ſperando erigitur, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo perficitur,</hi> (ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">Nemo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>putet bona opera ſua aute fidem: vbi ſides non erat, bonum opus non erat, Aug. lib. <hi>50.</hi> hom. homil. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſten</hi>) that is, The foundation of Gods houſe in our ſoules is faith, the walles, hope, the roofe, loue and good life.</p>
            <p>Wee deteſt and abiure that error of<note n="m" place="margin">Aug. haereſ. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Manicheus,</hi> who thought God made the ſoule, but not the body: So the Papiſts would make the world beleeue, that wee ſo build faith in the ſoule, as if wee profeſſed our ſelues Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines in the body, or were Nudifidians, &amp; carnal Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers, as they are Nullifidians, and Merit-mungers. No, a good faith, and a good life bee inſeparable, like <hi>Harpocrates</hi> twinnes, liue and die together. Faith goes before, good life followes: ſo<note n="n" place="margin">Aug. de fide, &amp; operib. c. <hi>7.</hi> Quicquid ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ur homo ex ſe, naledictae ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> malus eſt fructis, Aug. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Ioan. Ser. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſten, Niſi praecedat fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, vita bona ſequi non poteſt,</hi> that is, Vnleſſe faith goes before, good life cannot follow: and as it is a true and old ſaying in diuinity, Good workes follow him that is iuſtified,<note n="*" place="margin">Aug. lb. de fide &amp; operibus.</note> 
               <hi>Non praecedunt iuſtificandum,</hi> that is, They doe not goe before hee is iuſtified. We doe not hold that an hiſtoricall faith iuſtifies; but a liuely faith, which inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is ſeene to God, and outwardly ſhewed in good workes, and loue to our neighbours. Good workes, though they be not <hi>cauſa regnandi,</hi> that is, The cauſe to make vs raigne in Gods kingdome, yet they be <hi>via regni,</hi> the way to the kingdome: for though God will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs <hi>propter opera,</hi> that is, for our works, yet he will<note n="o" place="margin">Reu. 22.12 Rom. 2.6.</note> reward vs <hi>ſecundum opera,</hi> that is, according to our workes.</p>
            <p>And thus I haue a little exceeded my limits, (for I ſtudy not to be Controuerſall, but Doctrinall) in freeing our<note n="*" place="margin">Eccleſ. Angl. in Confeſſ. art. <hi>12.</hi> Iewels <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> part. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>20.</hi> Zanch. Comment. in <hi>1.</hi> Theſſ. <hi>4.</hi> Luth. Com. Epiſt. ad Gal. c. <hi>5.</hi> v. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Church-doctrine from the calumniations of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the grace of God, who like the Adder, ſtoppes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16348:26"/> his eare againſt the voice of the charmer, charme hee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo wiſely, or truely.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of all, is this: That wee were not able to redeeme our ſelues, nay, no Saints could ranſome vs, for<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 25.9.</note> they can ſpare no oyle for our lampes, no Angels re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme vs; for God layed folly on his<note n="q" place="margin">Iob. 4.18.</note> Angels: onely Chriſt Ieſus muſt bee the<note n="r" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.21</note> propitiation for ſinne, that knew no ſinne, who was <hi>made of a woman, and made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law,</hi> to redeeme vs from the curſe of the Law, and to iuſtifie vs by a liuely faith in him, and his merits, <hi>that we might receiue the adoption of Sonnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore to drawe to a concluſion:</p>
            <p>What ſhall we render vnto the Lord for all his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits beſtowed vpon vs? which benefits wee could not haue receiued but by Chriſts Incarnation.</p>
            <p>By it we haue a Kingdome, <hi>in poſſeſſionem,</hi> Poſſeſſe the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Matt. 25.34.</note> kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the world. His body <hi>in refectionem,</hi> that is, for our ſpirituall repaſt, My<note n="u" place="margin">Iohn 6.5.5.</note> fleſh is meat indeede: his blood, <hi>in abluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem,</hi> that is, for clenſing vs, he<note n="*" place="margin">Reu. 1.5.</note> waſheth vs from our ſinnes in his blood: his life, <hi>in redemptionem,</hi> for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; I<note n="x" place="margin">Ioh. 10.11.</note> lay downe my life for my ſheepe: his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity, <hi>in viſionem,</hi> to behold it, We<note n="y" place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12.</note> ſhall ſee him face to face: his eternity, <hi>in fruitionem,</hi> that is, in fruition,<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 17.3.</note> This is life eternall, that they may know thee to be the onely very God, and whom thou haſt ſent, Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Oh Beloued, had I the tongue of an Angell, or you the hearts of glorified Saints. I could not vtter, nor you conceiue the immeaſurable meaſure of diuine benefits we receiue by the Incarnation of our Sauiour: what ſhal we render for them? Let<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 115.12.13.</note> vs take the Cup of Saluation, and giue thankes, and prayſe the name of the Lord. Let vs imitate thoſe<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 2.11.</note> Wiſemen, <hi>Who hauing found the Babe, fell downe, and worſhipped him, and opened their Treaſures, and preſented gifts,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Auru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſolui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quaſi Regi magno, Thus immolatur vt Deo, Myrrha praebetur, vt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptori, &amp;c. Aug. in Ser. Epiphan.</note> 
               <hi>Gold, Incenſe, and Myrrh.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:16348:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</hi>
               <q>Aurum, Thus, Myrrham, Regique, homini<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Deo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dona ferunt</q> —that is,
<q>
                  <l>Gold, Frankincenſe, and Mirrhe, the Wiſemen offer</l>
                  <l>To him, as King, as man, as God th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y proffer.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So let vs fall downe, and worſhip this bleſſed Babe of Bethleem, and let vs offer gifts. Firſt, <hi>A liuely faith,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.7.</note> which is more precious then gold. Secondly, heartie Prayers, and Prayſes, which are as Incenſe vnto the Lord, like <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Reu. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>foure and twentie Elders, fall downe before the Lambe, hauing euery one Harpes, and golden Vials, which are the prayers of the Saints.</hi> Thirdly, Let vs offer Myrrhe, b tter, and contrite repentance for ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſinnes, conſidering that Chriſt, who is the fountaine of al good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, was for our ſinnes and ſakes accounted, (as<note n="d" place="margin">Luther. loc. com. tit. de Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti paſſione.</note> 
               <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> writes) <hi>Omnium poſſimus, reputatiuè coram hominibus, imputatiuè coram Deo,</hi> that is, as the worſt of all, by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation before men, by imputation before God, by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation before men. So the<note n="e" place="margin">Mark. 3.22</note> Scribes blaſphemed him, <hi>He hath Beelzebub:</hi> by Imputation before God; for all our ſinnes were imputed to him: <hi>Propter ſcelera noſtra attritus eſt,</hi> ſayth<note n="f" place="margin">Eſay 53.5.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay,</hi> that is, <hi>He was broken for our iniquities, and wounded for our tranſgreſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhal I ſay more? but with<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 1.29.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn Baptist, Ecce Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Dei,</hi> that is, behold the Lambe of God which takes away the ſinnes of the world. <hi>At this fulneſſe of time,</hi> God ſent this Lambe, (as a Lambe among Wolues) to redeeme, and to reduce to his fold the ſcattered flock of Iſrael: <hi>Redemptor noſter homo naſcendo, Agnus moriendo, Leo reſurgendo, Aquila aſcendendo factus eſt,</hi> (ſayth<note n="h" place="margin">Greg. hom. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie</hi>) that is, Our Redeemer made man by his Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſuffered as a Lambe in his paſſion, ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Lion of the Tribe of Iudah in his reſurrection, and mounted as a diuine Eagle in his Aſcenſion: and now<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>ſitteth at the right hand of his Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By his Incarnation we are regenerated, <hi>by his Paſſion
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16348:27"/> redeemed, by his Reſurrection reſtored from death to life, by</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 14.2.</note> 
               <hi>his Aſcenſion, he hath prepared an heauenly poſſeſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He was made of a woman,</hi> and made the Sonne of man, that we might be made the Sonnes of God, <hi>he was made vnder the law, and bond to the law, that we might be freed from the bendage of the law:</hi> Hee conquered the law by a double right, (as<note n="l" place="margin">Luther in textum.</note> 
               <hi>Luther</hi> writes) Firſt, as the Sonne of God, &amp; Lord of the Law. Secondly, in our perſon, which is as much, as if we had ouercome the law our ſelues; for his victorie is ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All this for our ſakes,</hi> that we might receiue the adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sonnes, and hath ſent the Spirit of his Sonne into our hearts, which cryeth, <hi>Abba Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let this meditation be euermore a Cordial of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, the <hi>aqua vitae,</hi> water of life to reuiue our ſinne-ſicke ſoules, and perplexed conſciences, againſt Sinne, Sathan, and the Law, which alwayes accuſe vs, terrifie vs, and condemne vs: let vs tell them boldly, that they haue no power ouer vs: for God the Father ſent his Sonne, <hi>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of a woman, and made vnder the Law,</hi> to redeeme vs from the curſe of the Law. Let vs creepe into that hole which bloody<note n="*" place="margin">Aug. Manuel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Longinus</hi> made with his ſpeare in our Sauiours ſide, there let vs hide our ſelues againſt our foes: let vs plunge our bleeding conſcience, in his bloody wounds, dolorous death, victorious reſurrection, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aſcenſion; and let vs firmely, and faithfully beleeue, that our Sauiour was borne, liued, died, roſe againe, and aſcended, that wee might rece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, and enioy the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the adoption of Sonnes.</p>
            <p>The dew of heauen, which fell vpon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eece of<note n="n" place="margin">Iudg. 6.38.</note> 
               <hi>Gedeon,</hi> fall downe vpon theſe our labours, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and water them with the dew of diuine grace in all your hearts, to his eternall glory, and your endleſſe comfort, and that for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, our onely Lord, Sauiour, and Redeemer: to whom, with the Father,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16348:28"/> and the holy Ghoſt, three perſons in Trinitie, one eternall God in vnitie, be aſcribed euerlaſting glory, might and Maieſtie, Dignitie, and Dominion, Prayſe, and Thankſgiuing world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Tri-vni Deo laus, &amp; gloria.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. MACCA. 15.39.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If I haue done well, and as the ſtory required, it is the thing that I deſired: but if I haue ſpoken ſlenderly, and bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is that I could.</p>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:16348:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
